<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>DATA4PT WIKI</sitename>
    <dbname>itptbinmwdata4pt</dbname>
    <base>https://data4pt.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.43.1</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">DATA4PT WIKI</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">DATA4PT WIKI talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Australia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>87</id>
    <revision>
      <id>603</id>
      <parentid>591</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-09-25T13:03:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anasfou</username>
        <id>5</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Anasfou moved page [[Draft:Australia]] to [[Australia]]</comment>
      <origin>591</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2297" sha1="7qpxif2q07gbxizrkbcw0fiuhy0ha8m" xml:space="preserve">== Use cases ==
The Department of Transport and Planning, located in the state of Victoria, Australia, is working on implementing NeTEx/GTFS for static data and SIRI/GTFS-R for real-time data. Currently, efforts are focused on obtaining endorsement for the technical specification documents related to NeTEx, GTFS, SIRI, and GTFS-R.

In addition, the process of formalizing data change notifications to operators for each of these standards is underway, and the data information requirements document is being finalized. This document will define the high-level roles and responsibilities between operators and the State.

=== Description ===
The state of Victoria has several modes of public transport which include train, tram and bus. They run in metropolitan areas of the city of Melbourne. Also, in regional towns in the state of Victoria.

To date, a vast majority of contracts that have been entered into between the Victoria State Government either are missing data exchange clauses or are limited in their application and are only suitable for single use cases. This has resulted in limited and inconsistent quality of data.

To ensure the Victoria State Government has an endorsed position relating to Public Transport (PT) data exchange standards governing how data is exchanged across the public transport eco-system.

=== Architecture ===

==== Future state ====
The diagram below is the planned target architecture for static and real-time public transport data.
[[File:Australia architecture.jpg|center|thumb|503x503px|Planned target architecture in Australia]]

=== Implementation ===
The State Government are working with Operators to embed these data standards into the contractual agreements for modes such as train, tram and bus.

The Department has managed to export NeTEx files from their development environments using the current timetable management system. 

GTFS data is currently being published out to third party apps like Google maps, and to the open data market. The Department are currently adding new data configurations based on MobilityData’s framework.

With SIRI and GTFS-R data they are currently being developed in a Proof of Concept (PoC).
=== Outcome ===
The expected results are a richer, consistent, and more accurate quality of public transport data.</text>
      <sha1>7qpxif2q07gbxizrkbcw0fiuhy0ha8m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Austria</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>77</id>
    <revision>
      <id>641</id>
      <parentid>639</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-12-11T12:26:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anonymous</username>
        <id>13</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added short description of wiener linien</comment>
      <origin>641</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4504" sha1="nrtmvo3l8ami23d0c3cx5gpcx78gxij" xml:space="preserve">== Overview in the National Level ==
For many implementations, the VDV standards (incl. VDV736) are preferred over other options, for them being tailored to the regional specifics.

[https://data.mobilitaetsverbuende.at/en MVO] publishes NeTEx data and preferably uses VDV736 (SIRI-SX) for situation information.

== Use cases ==

=== Description ===
'''Wiener Linien''' (Viennese Lines) is the company running most of the public transit network in the city of Vienna, Austria. Thus, it is responsible for managing the city's extensive network of buses, trams, and metro systems. It was established in 1978, and is part of the city corporation Wiener Stadtwerke. 

For the purposes of operating and maintaining customer information channels (such as the WienMobil app, digital signage and departure boards, the website, on-board information, etc.), Wiener Linien has introduced an API gateway as a middleware component. This ensures that all customer-facing channels source their information from a single system (the API gateway), providing consistent information across all available platforms.

=== Architecture ===
Since the data sources connected to the API Gateway may provide different formats, or the data required for "customer information" may be scattered across various independent sources, Wiener Linien has implemented SIRI and/or NeTEx as the canonical data formats within the API Gateway. This approach facilitates the consolidation of information within the API Gateway, ensuring it serves as the single point of truth for all customer information channels.

The API Gateway can provide customer information channels with data in the canonical format (SIRI or NeTEx) or transform the data into any format required by the consuming system.

For specific use cases, the data can be enriched before being provided to the customer information channels:

* Automatic translation of SIRI-SX Situation Descriptions
* Generation of sign language videos
* Creation of workload or delay estimates using machine learning

=== Implementation ===
The following use cases illustrate how Wiener Linien utilizes the API Gateway and data standards to operate and maintain customer information channels:

* '''FIS+''' involves on-board information screens in the latest subway rolling stock (X-Wagen). The necessary data, including station departures and current situations, is retrieved from internal data sources, transformed into the SIRI-SM and SIRI-SX canonical formats, and then converted into a proprietary format that contains only the most relevant information. This format is extremely lightweight due to limited bandwidth, and the information is subsequently forwarded to the rolling stock.

* For the '''WienMobil App and WienMobil Monitor''', the relevant information (station departures and current situations) is pulled from multiple data sources, including external sources from other transport operators like ÖBB. This data is transformed into the canonical SIRI-SM and SIRI-SX formats, cached within the API Gateway, and then delivered on demand to the app backend. The format is optimized by omitting redundant overhead to improve efficiency.
* The '''e-Paper timetable''' follows a similar process. Station departure and current situation data are pulled from internal data sources, transformed into SIRI-SM and SIRI-SX, cached within the API Gateway, and sent to the e-Paper backend as needed.
* For the generation of sign language videos, current situation data is regularly retrieved from internal sources, transformed into SIRI-SX, and sent a third party API. The thrid party system processes the situation descriptions, generating a sign language video for each relevant entry. A link to the video is returned and can be added as a custom field in any subsequent SIRI-SX messages.
* In the case of the WienMobil Alexa Skill, the required information (station departures) is sourced from internal and external data sources (such as ÖBB), transformed into SIRI-SM, cached in the API Gateway, and provided on demand to the backend system of the Alexa Skill.

=== Outcome ===
The chosen data standard framework is highly robust, accommodating virtually any use case. However, this flexibility introduces significant complexity, which can be challenging for some colleagues and implementers. Despite this, it is well-suited as a canonical data format for these reasons. With this framework in place, Wiener Linien is well-prepared to meet the requirements of EU Regulation 2017/1926.</text>
      <sha1>nrtmvo3l8ami23d0c3cx5gpcx78gxij</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Belgium</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>67</id>
    <revision>
      <id>619</id>
      <parentid>589</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-10-08T12:53:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Admin moved page [[Draft:Belgium]] to [[Belgium]]</comment>
      <origin>589</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="516" sha1="60tpo9zxwghbcf05dp2amjhtuy4fk47" xml:space="preserve">In Belgium, a national NeTEx profile has been defined, but it is currently not utilized by the Public Transport Operators (PTOs). Instead, there are existing NeTEx datasets available on the NAP in accordance with EU requirements, using EPIP. A converter has been employed to ensure compliance with these regulations. Recently, the Belgian PTOs have decided to adopt EPIP/EPIAP/EPIP-RT as their shared EU-compliant NeTEx/SIRI profiles. Work on producing and implementing these profiles is set to begin in autumn 2024.</text>
      <sha1>60tpo9zxwghbcf05dp2amjhtuy4fk47</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Croatia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>81</id>
    <revision>
      <id>601</id>
      <parentid>579</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-09-25T13:01:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anasfou</username>
        <id>5</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Anasfou moved page [[Draft:Croatia]] to [[Croatia]]</comment>
      <origin>579</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="6372" sha1="qnvb3cjudwdyl58d6tel64l0t6opiwr" xml:space="preserve">== Overview in the National Level ==
The national NeTEx profile of Croatia was created within the project of Implementation of NAP for multimodal traffic information and development of a local journey planner which took place in 2022 from March to November. 

The following documents were used to implement the Croatian national profile for NeTEx (also available via Croatian Institute for Standards). 

* CEN/TS 16614-1:2020 Public transport - Network and Timetable Exchange (NeTEx) - Part 1: Public transport network topology exchange format. 
** “white paper” NeTEx-Network-WhitePaper_1.08 which describes NeTEx network concept in a non-expert way. 
* CEN/TS 16614-2:2020 Public transport - Network and Timetable Exchange (NeTEx) - Part 2: Public transport scheduled timetables exchange. 
** “white paper” 09.NeTEx-Timetable-WhitePaper_1.05 which describes NeTEx timetable in a non-expert way.
* CEN/TS 16614-4:2020 Public transport - Network and Timetable Exchange (NeTEx) - Part 4: Passenger Information European Profile.


Within the project of Implementation of NAP for multimodal traffic information and development of a local journey planner, an internal tool was created to convert GTFS files to NeTEx due to the lack of PTA/PTO providers that have a machine-readable format.

Some of the PTA/PTO providers are on the national and some on regional level, and due to various completeness of data provided we had issues with compliance. 

Besides city centres, Croatia can be divided in three areas, central, maritime, and mountainous regions. From the perspective of data quality and available applications, central and maritime areas are more covered with quality data than mountainous region since they are driven by greater touristic demand. 

Level of digitalization of PTA/PTO data is rather low. Where exist, different standards are used, with GTFS prevailing as the most used data format. Further activities must be made in order to raise the level of data digitalisation within stakeholders, to hold the stakeholders to recognize benefits of data sharing and to ensure provision in EU support and recommended formats. Croatia has already started several projects in order to fulfil goals, with results already being visible with inclusion of more data sources in standardized format in Croatian NAP.

The basic concepts for EPIP are described in the data dictionary in CEN/TS 16614-4: 2020 Public transport - Network and Timetable Data Exchange (NeTEx) - Part 4: Passenger Information European Profile.

The main terminology used to describe the topology of the public transport network are:

* ROUTE: an ordered list of discrete locations as a route point that geographically defines a single route passing through a road (or rail) network.  ROUTE can pass through the same point of the route multiple times. ROUTE LINK can be used to connect ROUTE POINT points along the way.
* JOURNEY PATTERN: defined as an organized SCHEDULED STOP POINT (e.g. '''teyes''' where passengers enter and exit) and TIMING POINTS (i.e.  information on the time required for the preparation of timetables) on each ROUTE describing the pattern of operation of public transport vehicles. Journey Pattern can go through the same point multiple times.
* TIMING PATTERN: redo sequence TIMING POINTS for each JOURNEY PATTERN determined by TIMING PATTERN.  The sequence scheduled stop points (from journey pattern) is determined by the SERVICE PATTERN.  Service Pattern (= variant ROUTE) is a subset of a JOURNEY PATTERN consisting of a stop point sequence.

A line (LINE) is usually defined as the sum of multiple ROUTEs with a public label (name, number).  From a topological point of view ROUTS are usually very similar because the versions are basic ROUTE with some deviations. Two routes that share the same infrastructure path (or parallel path), but with the opposite orientation usually belong to the same LINE.

An XML document is a physical record of public passenger transport data used for the exchange between sender and recipient of EPIP-compliant data.

It is recommended that the XML document name be written as follows:

* The name of the document (prefix) is NETEX_PI
* The main version of EPIP; currently 01
* ISO 3166-2 Country Code
* Sender name (use NAP if data comes from National access point)
* Document type (LINE, NETWORK , or STOP)
** LINE: The document contains a description of one line: line number or name if no number is available (short name, fewer than 15 characters, made only of letters (uppercase and lowercase), numbers and "-")
** NETWORK: Document contains a description of two or more lines
** STOP: Document contains a description of all stops

* Date Created (YYMMDD)

* All fields are separated by a "_" character.

== Use cases ==
During the implementation of the NAP for multimodal traffic information and the development of a local journey planner, GTFS files were primarily transposed into NeTEx files. Currently, at NAP, data from several PTA/PTO providers (GPP Osijek, ZET, Pulapromet – bus, HŽ – train, and Jadrolinija – ferry) are available in the NeTEx standard. Additionally, the LJP was developed with all available PTA/PTO data. More information are accessible [https://www.promet-info.hr/ljp/?lang=en here].

In Croatia, the following projects utilize NeTEx and Datex standards:

* '''Smart City Rijeka, City of Rijeka - CEKOM Project''': Application of NeTEx and Datex standards for traffic management and passenger information.
* '''OLGA Green and Holistic Airport, City of Zagreb''': Application of NeTEx and Datex standards for traffic management and public transport optimization.
* '''Traffic Management System, City of Split''': Application of NeTEx and Datex standards for traffic management and passenger information.

=== Outcome ===
Most NAP users have expressed a strong interest in accessing PTA/PTO data, making it essential to ensure that all data available on NAP is updated in a timely manner, which is not always the case currently. 

The implementation results have facilitated easier data exchange among various stakeholders. The harmonization of standards has led to the development of uniform applications, reducing the need for integrating non-standard data from third-party providers. This has decreased application development costs and increased the reusability of applications.</text>
      <sha1>qnvb3cjudwdyl58d6tel64l0t6opiwr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Denmark</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>99</id>
    <revision>
      <id>618</id>
      <timestamp>2024-10-08T12:50:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anasfou</username>
        <id>5</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Created page with "== Overview in the National Level == [[File:Map DK.png|thumb|397x397px|Map of Denmark, with a focus on Greater Copenhagen]]  === NeTEx and SIRI profiles === In Denmark, EU profiles for NeTEx and SIRI has been adopted. The implementation follows the European standards to ensure compatibility and data quality for journey planning and real-time information services.   Guidance on the national requirements and best practices is available in Danish through Trafikstyrelsen, th..."</comment>
      <origin>618</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4148" sha1="pjq7gptv2gwl0pmrxsufca8yobzkm9u" xml:space="preserve">== Overview in the National Level ==
[[File:Map DK.png|thumb|397x397px|Map of Denmark, with a focus on Greater Copenhagen]]

=== NeTEx and SIRI profiles ===
In Denmark, EU profiles for NeTEx and SIRI has been adopted. The implementation follows the European standards to ensure compatibility and data quality for journey planning and real-time information services. 

Guidance on the national requirements and best practices is available in Danish through Trafikstyrelsen, the [https://www.trafikstyrelsen.dk/arbejdsomraader/kollektiv-trafik/statistik-og-data/krav-til-udstilling-af-data-til-rejseplanlaegning Danish Civil Aviation and Railway Authority], who is responsible for the implementation of NeTEx, SIRI and NAP on national level. For guidance in English, you can reach out to eudata@trafikstyrelsen.dk.

== Use cases ==
In Denmark two main stakeholders implement NeTEx and SIRI currently: 

# '''Movia'''. It is the PTA for buses and (certain) local trains in Greater Copenhagen. Other PTAs in this area are DSB (regional trains and S-trains) and Metro (Copenhagen metro and a tram line under construction).
# '''Rejsekort &amp; Rejseplan A/S'''. It is the company behind the national travel planner and electronic ticketing system in Denmark, which unites all regions and different transport operators into a common system.

=== Description ===

==== Rejsekort &amp; Rejseplan ====
Rejsekort &amp; Rejseplan A/S have used the NeTEx and SIRI standards nationwide, providing comprehensive coverage of the entire public transport network.

The architecture implemented by Rejsekort &amp; Rejseplan A/S relies on centralized data exports from subcontractors IVU Traffic Technologies and HaCon, which supply the necessary data to Rejsekort and Rejseplan. These systems use the NeTEx and SIRI profiles to ensure high compatibility and data consistency. This architecture allows for the effective aggregation of transport data across various operators and regions, supporting both journey planning and real-time passenger information services.

==== Movia ====
Movia is using NeTEx and SIRI as the main interfaces around a new ‘Traffic Management System’ TMS. The delivery of the TMS was tendered and the contract was awarded FARA in 2023 and is expected to be in operation in 2025.

The system will handle all PT bus and local train traffic within Greater Copenhagen and Sealand:

* Number of ServiceJourneys on a workday: ~20 000
* Number of Calls on a workday: ~700 000
* Number of concurrent journeys in rush hour: ~1 000
* Number of active stops (Quays): ~17 000

=== Architecture ===

==== Movia ====
The TMS will consume stops and schedules in NeTEx-format. We use a profile based on the [https://enturas.atlassian.net/wiki/spaces/PUBLIC/pages/728891481/Nordic+NeTEx+Profile Nordic Profile] with minor adaptions.

The system will expose NeTEx as well as SIRI data. NeTEx will be exposed using the Nordic-based profile as well as EPIP. 
[[File:Data providers.png|center|thumb|589x589px|TMS solution]] 

=== Use cases ===
Currently, there are no active users of NeTEx and SIRI. The national travel planner already provides comprehensive and well-functioning services across the country, and the introduction of these standards has not been able to contribute to any improvement.

=== Outcome ===
Movia is currently using a system based on NOPTIS interfaces. The choice of NeTEx/SIRI for the new system was driven by the fact that NOPTIS is only supported by few suppliers – NeTEx/SIRI are supported by EU, has status as CEN/TS, and are widely supported. We believe that the choice of NeTEx/SIRI has opened the competition with lower price as a result. Moreover, Movia expects that with NeTEx/SIRI, it will be easier to integrate new consumers in the future.

As of now, no significant benefits from the implementation of NeTEx and SIRI have been observed in Denmark. 

The largest Danish public transport authority is in the process of implementing NeTEx and SIRI, which may create new opportunities for enhanced data exchange and service improvements in the future. The full potential of these standards, however, has yet to be realized in Denmark.</text>
      <sha1>pjq7gptv2gwl0pmrxsufca8yobzkm9u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Draft:Czech Republic</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>86</id>
    <revision>
      <id>567</id>
      <timestamp>2024-09-17T11:10:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anonymous</username>
        <id>13</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Created page with "== Overview in the National Level ==  == Use cases ==  === Description ===  === Architecture ===  === Use cases ===  === Outcome ==="</comment>
      <origin>567</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="132" sha1="gyexpocm6pt24fqduffv1mds82kenxv" xml:space="preserve">== Overview in the National Level ==

== Use cases ==

=== Description ===

=== Architecture ===

=== Use cases ===

=== Outcome ===</text>
      <sha1>gyexpocm6pt24fqduffv1mds82kenxv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Explore NAP guidelines</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5</id>
    <revision>
      <id>718</id>
      <parentid>717</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-04-28T14:27:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anasfou</username>
        <id>5</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Abbreviations and Acronyms */</comment>
      <origin>718</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="41433" sha1="p388aefoewown1nmssa2rygjjpixtzx" xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:Explore NAP Guidelines}}

A National Access Point (NAP) is a central internet resource from which transport data for a country can be obtained by operators and third parties.

*A NAP may comprise a repository of reference data and/or a registry of available data services and real-time feeds.
*Data can be of many different types, both static - operators, lines, stops, timetables, accessibility, etc. and real-time (vehicle locations, estimated arrival times, disruptions, etc.)
*A NAP will hold metadata about the available data and feeds so as to be able to support search and discovery processes.

A number of standard formats and APIs, such as NeTEx, DatexII, SIRI are mandated.



Check the [https://data4pt-project.eu/ DATA4PT website]  and [https://napcore.eu/ NAPCORE website] for additional information.

= How to make datasets for multimodal mobility systems interoperable across the EU =
''Legal Disclaimer''

''The information in this document is provided “as is”, and no guarantee or warranty is given that the information is fit for any particular purpose. The referenced consortium members shall have no liability to third parties for damages of any kind including without limitation direct, special, indirect, or consequential damages that may result from the use of these materials subject to any liability which is mandatory due to applicable law. This document is published under the CC BY-SA 4.0 license&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;.''
----&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; See &lt;nowiki&gt;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.en&lt;/nowiki&gt;

== Summary ==
This paper proposes some best practices for National Access Points (NAPs) to follow for a better implementation of MMTIS Delegated Regulation (EU 2017/1926 and its amendment EU/2024/490). Based on the exchanges with the different stakeholders and on the overall experience acquired in the framework of DATA4PT, its experts’ team presents the main reasons why interoperability is hard to achieve, and how NAPs need to move forward to achieve their goals (goals as set by the regulation). It provides recommendations on overcoming these issues and building a common implementation approach of the regulations across the EU for multimodal mobility services advancement. 

NAPs need to be oriented beyond the local level and specific mobility mode. Integration from all perspectives (from city or region up to EU and worldwide, from one mobility mode to full inter-modality) is key. As the goal is more sustainable mobility in the long run (financially, environmentally, socially), complete and inclusive data standards to support all chains of data exchange from operations to end user/passenger are the main tools for this. 

The target group of this paper is the NAP implementers and operators and the organisations regulating them in their country. This paper can be used as reference from stakeholders whenever it is relevant and to complement the work done in the framework of the NAPCORE Programme.

The most important aspects addressed in this paper could be summarised in the following recommendations:

●       The data in all NAPs is at least published according to one profile per standard required by the regulation.  

●       NAPs should also consume the data it shares. It also should encourage data producers to consume the data it produces (e.g. using digital twinning as a method. Also, the NAPs should collaborate within NAPCORE to make the interfaces generic (applicable to all NAP), open source and shared between NAPs).

●       A stop registry must be provided.

●       The NAPs should give incentives to data producers to provide correct data. 

●       The following standards shall be used: NeTEx (schedules, stop registry, fares), SIRI (real-time), OJP (API towards a Journey Planner), OpRa and in general the ones based on Transmodel (CEN standard).&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;

●       The NAPs should maintain all neighboring NAP references so end-users can directly find the relevant datasets for cross-border operation.

●       The NAPs should actively register successful integrations, their products, and the source datasets that were used. This will automatically give a graph of importance.  

●       In addition, other formats/ specifications shall be shared in NAPs if useful by data consumers like GTFS/GBFS. The standards should have good governance&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;.
----&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; NeTEX = TS16614, SIRI = TS/EN 15531, OJP = TS 17118

&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt; E.g. see ISO - Good Standardization Practices (GSP)

== What to expect from this paper ==
This paper proposes some best practices for National Access Points (NAPs) to follow for a better implementation of MMTIS Delegated regulation (EU 2017/1926 and the amendment EU/2024/490), NAPs need to focus on the data consumers and easy access to the data for them. Only complete, homogenised, integrated data sets are of interest. Quality assurance needs to be an integral part of all NAPs. NAPs need to be oriented beyond the local level and specific mobility mode. Relevant is integration from all perspectives (from city or region up to EU and worldwide, from one mobility mode to full inter-modality). As the goal is more sustainable mobility in the long run (financially, environmentally, socially), complete and inclusive data standards to support all chains of data exchange from operations to end user/passenger are the main tools for this. 

Based on the exchanges with the different stakeholders and on the overall experience acquired in the framework of DATA4PT, its experts’ team presents the main reasons why interoperability is not yet achieved, and how NAPs need to move forward to achieve their goals (goals as set by the regulation). It provides recommendations on how to overcome these issues and build a common implementation approach of the regulations across the EU for multimodal mobility services advancement. This paper can be used as a reference for stakeholders whenever it is relevant and to complement the work done in the framework of NAPCORE Programme.

=== To whom it addresses ===
The target group is the NAP implementers and operators and the organisations regulating them in their country.

=== Objectives and expected outcome ===
The objectives of this paper can be summarised as follows: 

* Present the prerequisites and procedures to make datasets viable and interoperable.
* Make it easy for consumers of MMTIS (EU/2024/490 and EU/1926/2017) data to fetch the same data types from different NAPs without additional cost.
* Reflect on the work of other national and EU projects and initiatives (like NAPCORE).
* Support NAP operators and other actors in decision-making for adapting implementation to the guidelines to implement the MMTIS DR.

The expected outcome of the following paper’s recommendations is that:

* Make it simple to produce data to be published on a NAP.
* Make seamless cross-border mobility services and passenger information systems possible, reliable and viable.
* Data consumers can access the relevant data from all NAPs in a way that will promote the usage of NAP data for free.
* NAP knows how to provide data in an easy standardised way, so that data consumers don’t need or can greatly reduce additional business logic in their connectors.

* Homogenise the usage of NeTEx/SIRI (and simpler standards for convenience like GTFS and GBFS).
* Provide all necessary data on the national level according to MMTIS DR.

=== Principles&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; ===
This guidance document is developed with some principles to help the industry navigate toward our interoperable future. The principles are statements of intent that lay out the MMTIS’s positive vision for the future of mobility data. Rooted in the philosophies of public service and personal empowerment that define the transit industry, the principles also highlight the efficiency, connectivity, and flexibility that interoperability will unlock for mobility data users.

# CEN-Standards: Interoperability should be achieved through the development, adoption, and widespread implementation of NeTEx and SIRI data that support the efficient exchange and portability of mobility data.
# Cross-border alignment: We seek collaboration within the NAPs and CEN to secure easy-to-use cross-border open data from the National Access Points; we align on as few profiles as possible.
# Interoperability: It is highly recommended that all systems creating, modifying, or consuming mobility data should be interoperable.
# Tools: Transit agencies and other mobility service providers should have access to tools that present high-quality mobility data accessibly, equitably, and in real time to assist travelers in meeting their mobility needs.
# Open technology: Transit agencies, other mobility service providers, and travelers should be able to select the transportation technology components that best meet their needs.
# High quality: All individuals and the public should be empowered through high-quality, always updated, well-distributed mobility data to find, access, and utilize high-quality mobility options that meet their needs as they see fit while maintaining their privacy.
# Self-utilization: The NAPs and data producers should, when possible, use the shared data themselves.

----&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; Inspired by: &lt;nowiki&gt;https://www.interoperablemobility.org/&lt;/nowiki&gt;

== What hinders interoperability ==
Interoperability is not an easy goal to achieve. On a national level, many of the countries harmonised their approaches to publish data in the NAP according to the regulation and they are developing services to use this data to provide country-based passengers’ services. However, in most cases, there are still challenges to overcome to make the available data useful for cross-regional or intermodal journeys, while cross-country services are still not possible due to the following parameters: 

●       Master data management and strategies for stop identifiers (IDs) that ensures stable and unique IDs are not always in place.

●       Exported data is of poor quality (if available at all), as if the data itself was not used.

●       NAPs don’t always aggregate the data and take a role in quality assurance.

●       Data completeness is not documented.

●       The standards are still poorly implemented in some countries

●       The standards themselves are not strict enough. Even the profiles have too much ambivalence.

●       Different profiles are used in different countries and are not interoperable (i.e. NOT based on EU profiles).

●       IDs are not coherent between neighbouring regions of the dataset, within and across NAPs; for both the same data theme (i.e. public transport between countries) as well as across themes (i.e. street network to public transport).

●       Data processes in the NAPs are not documented.

●       Duplication in data content.

Chapters 4 and 5 address these points in detail. The MMTIS data dictionary, which is being developed in the framework of NAPCORE project&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;, will also help. The development of the NeTEx and SIRI European profiles will also help unlock interoperability.
----&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; MMTIS Data dictionary from NAPCORE project: &lt;nowiki&gt;https://github.com/NAPCORE/Data-dictionary/blob/main/DR%20(EU)%202024-490.md&lt;/nowiki&gt;

== Most important points ==
The following points are important for all NAPs.

* The data in all NAPs are at least published according to the relevant European profile per standard defined by the regulation (other additional data formats may help adoption in the field).
* NAPs should also be prepared to consume the data they share. It also should encourage each data producer to consume the data it produces. E.g. a digital twin can be formed that consumes this data and presents it as an example to the user.
* Access to consistent information on the European level for all stops (NeTEx: StopPlace) and quays (NeTEx: Quays). A stop registry on EU level should be the final goal. 
* The NAPs should incentivise data producers to provide correct data: complete, quality-assured, and valid on syntactic and semantic levels. E.g. by checking it themselves (as e.g. the French NAP does for GTFS).
* The NAPs should maintain, in addition to their own data, some data or at least metadata for relevant adjacent NAPs so end-users may directly find the relevant datasets for cross-border operation.
* The following standards shall be used: NeTEx (stop registry, schedules, fares), SIRI (real-time), OJP (API to a journey planner), and in general the ones based on Transmodel (CEN standard). Also OpRa as soon as it is available.
* In addition, other formats/ specifications might be shared in NAPs if useful by data consumers like GTFS/GBFS
* The standards should be open&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; and have good governance.
* Work to harmonize the national profiles to become unified. 

----&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; This is related to the decision of the Court of Justice of the European Union (CURIA) about the access conditions to “harmonised standards adopted by CEN that form part of EU Regulations”. Link to the case law [https://curia.europa.eu/juris/documents.jsf?nat=or&amp;mat=or&amp;pcs=Oor&amp;jur=C%2CT%2CF&amp;num=C-588%252F21P&amp;for=&amp;jge=&amp;dates=&amp;language=en&amp;pro=&amp;cit=none%252CC%252CCJ%252CR%252C2008E%252C%252C%252C%252C%252C%252C%252C%252C%252C%252Ctrue%252Cfalse%252Cfalse&amp;oqp=&amp;td=%3BALL&amp;avg=&amp;lgrec=fr&amp;page=1&amp;lg=&amp;cid=740237 here].

=== Why Transmodel based standards in NAPs ===
The reference data model Transmodel is required by the MMTIS EU DR due to several reasons. 

The most important parameter that makes Transmodel the choice of the regulation is the fact that it is a conceptual model which provides common language and  data structures to describe semantics of the Public Transport domain. It considers a number of public transport features for information and service management and it includes concepts, their characteristics and links between concepts. It  describes aspects covered by conventional public transport, including flexible transport and alternative modes​ and it allows interoperability between the information processing systems of transport operators without the need of conversion. Like this it facilitates the representation of multimodal trips, without the risk of losing information along the data chain and it can be used to design databases and/or data exchange formats. In fact, Transmodel has been used for many years to specify a number of CEN data exchange formats, such as CEN SIRI (for real-time data), CEN NeTEx(for planned data) and OpRa (for operational raw data) (Figure 1). It is published under the reference number EN12896 as series EN12896 1 to 10 (Figure 2).

[[File:Figure 1 Illustration of the interactions between Transmodel SG4 and WG3 subgroups SG7 for SIRI, SG8 for OJP SG9 for NeTEx SG10 for OpRa (Source-https---transmodel-cen.eu-)..jpg|thumb|Figure 1 Illustration of the interactions between Transmodel SG4and WG3 subgroups SG7 for SIRI, SG8 for OJP, SG9 for NeTEx, SG10 for OpRa (Source:https://transmodel-cen.eu/).]]


[[File:Figure 2 Transmodel Parts and relation with the different technical standards exchange formats and APIs.jpg|thumb|Figure 2 Transmodel Parts and relation with the different technical standards exchange formats and APIs (Source:https://transmodel-cen.eu/).]]

===	How CEN European Standards are developed and how to contribute as NAP operator ===

Transmodel and its data exchange formats are developed under the aegis of CEN (Comité Européen de Normalisation). The development of the standards is based on the involvement of all relevant stakeholders for multimodality (beyond silos) and the official approval process is based on votes from representatives from all CEN members. 
European standards have also been developed to ease compliance with European rules and regulations such as EU legislation. Through Regulation (EU) No 1025/2012, the three European Standardisation Organisations (CEN, CENELEC and ETSI) may receive a request to produce European harmonised standards in support of EU legislation and policies (more here).
Technically anyone can propose work items that will result in a European Standard. Actually, an expert (e.g. from a NAP) in the field can request through its CEN national standardisation body to be part of the group TC278/WG3, following the national rules. At CEN and CENELEC the work is usually channeled by the members (the CEN National Standardization Bodies and the CENELEC National Committees). In some cases, the request also comes from the European Commission or from other stakeholders.
If enough CEN and/or CENELEC members are willing to be involved in the development process, the work is then assigned to the relevant Technical Committee (TC). At the same time, a “standstill” is enforced in all national work surrounding the same topic. Once the Technical Committee is established, mirror committees of stakeholders at national level decide on the national contributions regarding the development of the standard. In addition to the CEN and/or CENELEC members, Technical Committees also include several observers, such as ISO/IEC members, European Commission/EFTA, external European industry associations and other affiliate bodies.

[[File:Figure 3 CEN Technical Committees TCs split into Working Groups.jpg|thumb|Figure 3 CEN Technical Committees TCs split into Working Groups (Source:https://transmodel-cen.eu/).]]


Transmodel is developed by TC 278 WG3 (Public Transport). Its structure is presented in figure 4.

[[File:Figure 4 TC 278 WG3 Public Transport structure.jpg|thumb|Figure 4 TC 278 WG3 Public Transport structure (Source:https://transmodel-cen.eu/)]]

TC 278 WG3 splits on its turn into Sub-Groups (SGs) as shown in the picture below (Figure 5).  

[[File:Figure 5. TC 278 WG3 Public Transport structure.jpg|thumb|Figure 5. TC 278 WG3_Public Transport structure (Source: https://transmodel-cen.eu/)]]Once the proposal for a standard has been evaluated and approved, the proposal goes on to the drafting stage which is based on consensus-building. When the draft standard is finalised, it goes up to public inquiry and is open to all interested parties. When the enquiry is over, the votes and comments on the standard are evaluated and depending on the result, the draft standard is either published or additionally worked upon and subsequently submitted to a formal vote.  Each of the Transmodel standards has a discussion forum on basecamp (by invitation). The physical standards NeTEx, SIRI and OJP have also an open GitHub-repository where questions and changes requests can be raised. The GitHub repositories are:
* VDV/OJP: [https://github.com/VDVde/OJP Open API for distributed journey planning]
* NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx: [https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx/ Network Timetable Exchange]  
* SIRI-CEN/SIRI: [https://github.com/SIRI-CEN/SIRI Service Interface for Real time Information (SIRI)]

Read more regarding CEN processes and standards development: https://www.cencenelec.eu/european-standardization/european-standards/

=== How to acquire Transmodel based standards ===

The documentation of the standards is made available by the national standardisation bodies&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;, following their process and using the corresponding identification numbers of each document: 

* Transmodel standard (EN12896 1-10) 
* SIRI-Service interface for Real-time Information, CEN EN/TS 15531 1-7 (SG7)
* NeTEx: Network, Timetables and Fare Exchange, CEN TS 16614 1-6 (SG9)
* Open API for Distributed Journey Planning, CEN TS 17118 (SG8)
* Data Communication on Vehicles, CEN TS 13149 7-11 (SG1)
* OpRa: Operational Raw Data and Statistics, under development (SG10)

For the purposes that this document tries to promote, it would be an advantage if these standards were made available free of charge.                

There is an ongoing discussion if there is a legal obligation to provide free access to CEN standards that are referred to in laws and regulations according to the principle of “free access to all that is a law”.

The standards have related technical artifacts, like UML, XSD, libraries, profiles, and open source, that are available for free at various websites. These documents should cover the need when developing a software to support MMTIS. The websites where technical artifacts are available are:

* &lt;nowiki&gt;https://transmodel-cen.eu/&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* &lt;nowiki&gt;https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN&lt;/nowiki&gt; 
* &lt;nowiki&gt;https://github.com/SIRI-CEN/SIRI&lt;/nowiki&gt; 
* &lt;nowiki&gt;https://github.com/VDVde/OJP&lt;/nowiki&gt; 

----&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; To browse the documents, you may use this [https://standards.cencenelec.eu/dyn/www/f?p=CEN:105::RESET:: tool].Regulation (EC) No 1049/2001 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 30 May 2001 regarding public access to European Parliament, Council and Commission documents is available [https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg/2001/1049/oj here].

== Recommendations ==

This chapter addresses specific areas to improve the interoperability and usefulness of NAPs according to chapters 2 and 3 and details parts of chapter 4.

=== Focus on users ===
The NAPs should keep their data consumers in focus. The data and API that NAP provides need to fulfill the use cases of those consumers. It should also make life easier for data producers. Some points to consider are:

* NAPs should provide easy and free access to the data for the users, including references to the documentation of the data standards and API used.
* The integration of the data of a NAP should be straightforward and cheap for producers and consumers.
* The same data pipelines of producers and consumers should work for all NAPs (no additional adaptation needed). This means that data, formats, and authorization must work straightforwardly.
* The data should be integrated and harmonised within a NAP. This means e.g. that aggregated timetables are provided.

* The NAPs should be able to detect and inform about quality problems in the data flows (mistakes, incompleteness, delayed delivery).

* The NAPs should actively pursue registering successful integrations, their results, and the source datasets used. This will automatically give a graph of importance. And visibility for new products and innovations.
* The NAPs should provide an open issue tracker to report data problems.
* The NAPs should provide a Quality-of-Service statement for its operation.
* The NAPs should provide cross-references to relevant other datasets that are temporal or spatial in nature. The new timetable of next year, the timetable of a neighbouring region, or an adjacent data theme.
* Simple format output: Many use cases can be covered by simpler data formats. The NAPs should generate those from the input stream (e.g. provide a GTFS in addition to NeTEx).
* Cross-border integration must be supported from the shared data. The NAP should keep in mind that cross-border integration will occur with their data sets. The way to do it should be documented. The best would be to use the same ID for lines, journeys and stops in all shared data and that it is supported in all local systems. Referencing is better than mapping.
* No special data licenses should be used. The data should be open data with neither (mandatory) registration nor legal restrictions. A regular well documented open data license should be used.
* Full metadata on each API and dataset should be provided (e.g. [https://napcore.eu/metadata/#:~:text=mobilityDCAT%2DAP%20provides%20precise%20and,for%20data%20portals%20in%20Europe. mobilityDCAT-AP] )
* Links to data usage description, tools, libraries and base information should be provided with the data. The description should be written for user consumption.

=== General guidance for responsibilities of a NAP&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; ===
The NAP is not only a simple meta data catalogue. Otherwise, it will never fulfill the needs of a European mobility data space. Some essential issues NAP needs to address:

* The NAP is responsible for delivering all necessary EU/1926/2017 data to consumers. The current situation should be shown.
* The data is provided in a homogenised, quality-assured way in standard formats.
* The NAP is responsible for upstream communication about quality issues.
* The NAP makes quality issues with data sets public.
* The NAP provides documentation about the data.
* The NAP is responsible for the metadata of all data sets.
* The NAP must provide a Quality of Service for the data.
* The NAP gives guidance on the relevant ID and master data management.
* The NAP is responsible for the governance of the mobility data space it spans.
* The NAP should encourage and even require native NeTEx and SIRI from the source system. 
* When the source only provides GTFS, the NAP shall harmonize the ID structure to a national context and provide GTFS. The NAP should not convert GTFS to NeTEx, instead it should give incentives to the data producer to deliver native NeTEx. 
* From the collected NeTEx and SIRI data, the NAP should provide data on less comprehensive formats like GTFS and GTFS RT. 

----&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; This document, in general, reflects the point of view of DATA4PT experts’ team. Then NAPCORE role (and MS) can use this document or not to make decisions on how to align and improve a NAP.

=== General guidance on standards and profiles ===
The updated Delegated Regulation (EU/2024/490) highlights the connection between profiles and data categories in Articles 4 and 5. It specifies that data should be represented using either minimum EU profiles or national profiles. This guide provides recommendations for parties interested in creating and implementing national profiles in alignment with the Delegated Regulations.

==== Key recommendations for developing national profiles ====
1.    Align with the European profile:

○     National profiles must adhere to the European profile to ensure consistency and interoperability across countries.

2.    Collaborate on a joint maximum profile:

○     National Access Points (NAPs) should work together to create a shared maximum profile for Europe.

○     The EU profile must be fully interoperable (1:1) with this joint maximum profile.

3.    Avoid profile proliferation:

○     Check existing national profiles before creating a new one.

○     Collaborate with other countries to develop a profile that meets shared needs.

4.    Process for developing a national profile: If a new national profile is necessary, follow these steps (see Section 5.5 for details):

○     Define the functional scope: Determine the essential requirements and exclude unnecessary elements.

○     Assess existing profiles: Check whether any European or national profiles already meet your needs. Contact CEN experts to explore collaboration opportunities.

○     Develop a new profile (if needed): If no existing profiles are suitable and collaboration is not possible, use the standard to create a new profile. If additional information is required beyond the European profile

* Check if the needed elements already exist in the full standard. If so, add them to the national profile.
* If the elements do not exist, propose and specify extensions to the European minimum profile. Coordinate with the organization responsible for the standard to integrate these extensions.

==== Practical considerations ====
1.    Interoperability:

○     Ensure European profiles enable easy information exchange.

○     Extensions should allow seamless extraction of interoperable data.

2.    Resolve ambiguities in profiles:

○     NAPs should provide clear guidance and coordinate with other NAPs to resolve ambiguities uniformly across Europe.

3.    Expert consultation:

○     If unsure about profiles, consult expert groups responsible for the standards.

4.    Roadmap and documentation:

○     Maintain a roadmap for profile development and adherence.

○     Clearly document any differences in the profiles and ensure the NAP’s output aligns with them.

By following these guidelines, countries can develop national profiles that align with European standards, fostering interoperability and reducing redundancy across profiles.

=== Guidance for National NeTEx and SIRI profile ===
The data must be able to cover all possible use cases (UC):

* UC1: Publish data in a NAP to support cross-borders seamless mobility
* UC2: Publish data in a NAP to feed national operational or passenger information systems – to support interoperability at national level.
* UC3: Third-party users using data from a NAP can have the need for elements not in the interest for data producers and an NAP. Such data must be provided through an NAP as long as it is part of MMTIS and data exists in a machine-readable format.

The data should be able to cover possible following use cases:

* UC4: With added extra data, which is not needed for MMTIS, data producers can harvest positive outcomes by using richer data from the NAPs with increased quality in their internal systems.

NeTEx and Siri should be provided according to the relevant European profiles:

* EPIP:  NeTEx Part 4
* EPIAP: NeTEx Part 6
* Fares: NeTEx Part 7 (under development)
* SIRI European Profile: SIRI Part 7

Open data in the NAP should always follow the most recent or a tagged version from the GitHub repositories for SIRI and NeTEx.

Currently, EPIP is a minimal profile and holds the minimum of data needed for trip planning use, regards MMTIS DR.

There is a need for the NAPs to work towards having one single maximum profile in use&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;. If extensions in profile are needed, experts should be consulted so that all of Europe does the extension in the same way. If something is needed in EPIP an issue should be created in the issue tracker for EPIP&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;, NeTEx&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt; or SIRI&lt;sup&gt;[4]&lt;/sup&gt;. If changes in Transmodel are needed, the relevant CEN experts raise the question further to the Transmodel group.

Neither EPIP nor EPIAP define, if a single or multiple NeTEx files should be exported. The files should be structured for easy loading and validation.

Coverage: datasets should be as complete as possible for a given country or region. The degree of coverage/completeness should be declared per geographical region (e.g. country) in terms of percentages/fractions (e.g. “100 % of trains in country A are covered” and a description of which modes or operators that are missing).


The datasets must provide enough time into the future to allow for most use cases. For example, if tickets are sold up to 120 days in advance, then that is the time horizon that must always be available.


The data must be provided in a manner that allows for cross-region, cross-country integration (see also sections 1.5.7 and 1.5.9). The method of integration needs to be documented. The guidelines in the data dictionary should be followed as well.
----&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; Inspiration can be found in the Nordic Profile for NeTEx and SIRI, where Norway, Sweden, Finland and Denmark collaborate on one profile,  and datasets that we share is easy to use cross-border, while we add more data needed extending the EU-profile and MMTIS requirements or in the Swiss profile. 

&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt; See https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx-Profile-EPIP/issues 

&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt; See https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx/issues 

&lt;sup&gt;[4]&lt;/sup&gt; See https://github.com/SIRI-CEN/SIRI/issues

=== Guidance for availability of the data in NAP ===
For NeTEx datasets:

* Any changes of a timetable are available as soon as possible and at least before the day they start to apply.

For SIRI datasets:

* Provide at least SIRI-ET, SIRI-SX, SIRI-FM, SIRI-VM. 
* Provide a simple easily accessible request/response API (without requiring filters or subscriptions). A recommendation for event based access to the SIRI data is being worked on in relevant CEN TC 278 WG3 SG7.

=== Guidance for documentation ===
We clarify some points here:

* A NAP has two target audiences:: PTA or PTO that shall deliver data to the NAP and developers who will use the data. Provide two different sets of documentation.
* The meta information must be complete, and an evaluation must be made of whether the data will be useful for the use cases the users have in mind.
* The documentation also includes all relevant information about standards, profiles, XSD etc.
* Open API test environments should be provided.
* The documentation does not only describe technical details, but also how to use those.
* Example code/data is provided and explained.
* Special cases are laid out.
* Problems and workarounds should be addressed.
* The documentation should be provided in an open way.
* Documentation should provide best practices.
* NAP should align documentation with other NAPs.
* Documentation should be in English, other languages are optional.

=== Guidance for interoperability ===
This is only a short note, as most information is addressed in the other sections. When planning the data structures, the NAP should consider:

* The data sets should integrate with other data in the same NAP (id).
* It should integrate with data from other NAPs and data domains outside MMTIS.
* It should integrate cross-border data.

Referencing in those cases is always better than “mapping”. Therefore section 1.5.8 and 1.5.9 are rather important.

=== Guidance for geo-referencing ===
Coordinates should be provided for all elements that can be located. Altitude or level needs to be considered as well when relevant.

The NAP should consider that multiple geo-bases may be used.

If a local map projection is used, WGS84 (latitude, longitude) should still be provided as signed decimal numbers as well.

WGS84 should be provided with 5-6 digits after the comma.

If references exist, they should be mentioned in NeTEx as well (national geo-base and OSM).

=== Guidance for consistent IDs across datasets ===
To enable interoperability between datasets published in an NAP, consistent IDs for relevant elements (such as stop places) are needed. Then the elements can be referenced and there is no need for loss-full matching&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;. This approach results in the following best practices:

* Core elements (also mentioned in the MMTIS data dictionary) must have stable IDs. E.g. operators/business units, stops, lines, quays, journey, situation, train number.
* The ID should be globally unique, also between NAPs.
* IDs should be stable over time. 
* Changes to the core elements referenced mentioned above should be versioned.
* A unique and stable ID must be used in the NeTEx ID elements that refer to “real” objects (e.g. StopPlace, but not PassingTime). IDs or mapping tables relating to external systems should only be used ''outside'' the NeTEx data pipeline or be inserted as keyValue additional information..
* IDs of other NAPs (when stable and unique) are used and not overwritten.
* Data producers are responsible for keeping the master data updated (which means also the ID). The NAPs should be encouraged to provide a software platform to do so. The NAPs must do quality assurance and give feedback to the data producers.&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;
* IDs must, as far as possible, be the same in all relevant published files (all formats, SIRI, NeTEx, GTFS etc.)​. 
* The NeTEx documentation provides ideas on how to build a unique ID.
* Uniqueness of journey ID/train number is by operation day and across datasets and over time.
* The unique ID provided in the data from the NAP should be available to the local source data and systems for easy enhancements by a NAP data consumer.

----&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; Matching algorithms may do things wrongly. E.g. they can’t identify the correct line and create a new one or they match to the wrong stop (e.g. because the coordinates are not correct/ambiguous).

&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt; E.g. national stop registry, operator registry, line registry and also a validation pipeline and other services.

=== Improve collaboration by building ecosystem of coherent services ===
To enhance collaboration, data quality, and data usage in the common mobility data space, key software tools—such as validators, libraries, catalogs, and APIs—should be open-source. Since all NAPs face similar challenges, collaboration on software development is encouraged&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;, following guidelines like those from the Swiss government&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;.

Each NAP can choose how to develop its systems: by procuring software, hiring a team to develop open-source solutions, or developing open-source software in-house, or a combination of those. Regardless of the approach, procured and open-source systems should be able to work together.

Some countries, like Switzerland and Norway, believe that when this ecosystem is publicly funded, software and code—whether developed or procured— it should be openly available whenever possible&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;. They believe it ensures a cost-efficient, collaborative, and well-functioning system that provides high-quality open data, easily accessible across all NAPs in Europe.
----&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt; https://opensource.com/open-source-way

&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt; Swiss tools for open sourcing code in public administrations: https://www.bk.admin.ch/bk/en/home/digitale-transformation-ikt-lenkung/bundesarchitektur/open_source_software/hilfsmittel_oss.html 

&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt; See example from Entur https://github.com/entur
=== Guidance for the usage of non-Transmodel standards ===
NAP should provide datasets and services for standards widely adopted by large communities. It is also essential that NAP follows European regulations, though using conversion tools is, of course, accepted. However, it is strongly recommended that providers natively support EU formats, with NAP converting to other formats for dissemination purposes.

In cases where providers use other widely supported formats, it can be accepted that the conversion process falls under NAP's responsibility rather than the operators. Such conversions should be considered temporary. For instance, there is a vast ecosystem for GTFS and, for the micro-mobility sector, GBFS is widely used. The adoption of NeTEx/SIRI for micro-mobility is still in its early stages and could be supported and funded by countries. Many software systems already support GBFS and should extend that support to NeTEx/SIRI in the future. Necessary conversion steps can and should be handled by NAP or through tools provided by NAP.

Ideally, the mapping between these standards and the Transmodel ecosystem should already be in place, which is the case for both GBFS and GTFS.

●  [https://transmodel-cen.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/2024-June_DATA4PT_GTFS-NeTEx-Mapping_vf.pdf Outline comparison and Mapping between NeTEx and GTFS – June 2024]

●  [https://transmodel-cen.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Methodology-for-comparing-data-standards.pdf Methodology for comparing data standards – January 2020]

●  [https://transmodel-cen.eu/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/StandardsHarmonisation-2019-njsk-v1.0-1.pdf Report on Standards Harmonisation including a GTFS to Transmodel / NeTEx mapping – September 2019]

●  [https://data4pt.org/w/images/5/5b/Canonical_mapping_-_NeTEx_and_SIRI_new_modes_with_GBFS.pdf GBFS to NeTEx &amp; SIRI v1.0-  A canonical mapping produced by MobilityData and DATA4PT]

== Abbreviations and Acronyms ==
{| class="wikitable"
|DR
|Delegated Regulation
|-
|EPIAP
|European Passenger Information Accessibility Profile (NeTEx part  6)
|-
|EPIP
|European Passenger Information  Profile (NeTEx part 4)
|-
|MMTIS
|MultiModal Travel Information Services (EU 2017/1926 and the  amendment EU/2024/490)
|-
|MS 
|Members States
|-
|NAP
|National Access Point 
|-
|NeTEx
|Network Timetable Exchange
|-
|OPRA
|OPerating RAw data and statistics exchange
|-
|PTA 
|Public Transport Authorities
|-
|PTO 
|Public Transport Operators 
|-
|SIRI
|Service interface for real-time information
|-
|Source system
|The system producing the  data for the NAP. 
|-
|TRANSMODEL
|Public Transport Reference Data Model
|}

== Guidelines Control Sheet ==
{| class="wikitable"
|Type of documentation:
|'''Guidelines'''
|-
|Documentation responsible:
|Information  Technology for Public Transport (ITxPT)
|-
|Project/ Work package:
|DATA4PT/ WP3
|-
|Main editor:
|Matthias  Günter
|}
{| class="wikitable"
|'''Editors and contributors'''
|'''Organisation'''
|-
|'''Matthias Günter'''
|SBB and member of DATA4PT experts' team
|-
|'''Brede Dammen'''
|Entur and member of DATA4PT experts' team
|-
|'''Anastasia Founta'''
|ITxPT and DATA4PT project manager
|-
|Ulf  Bjersing
|Hogia and member of DATA4PT experts' team
|-
|Christophe Duquesne
|Consultant and member of DATA4PT experts' team
|-
|Emmanuel De Verdalle
|ITxPT and DATA4PT technical manager
|}
{| class="wikitable"
| colspan="4" |'''Guidelines Revision History'''
|-
| colspan="4" |'''Modifications Introduced'''
|-
|'''Version'''
|'''Date'''
|'''Reason'''
|'''Editor'''
|-
|'''0.0'''
|05/04/2024
|Draft  structure
|Anastasia  Founta
|-
|'''0.1'''
|20/06/2024
|Integration  of input 
|Matthias  Günter
Brede  Dammen
|-
|'''0.2'''
|30/06/2024
|Review 
|Matthias  Günter
Brede  Dammen

Ulf  Bjersing

Christophe Duquesne

Emmanuel De Verdalle
|-
|'''1.0'''
|31/6/2024 
|Final  editing
|Matthias  Günter
Brede  Dammen

Anastasia  Founta
|}
----</text>
      <sha1>p388aefoewown1nmssa2rygjjpixtzx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>FAQ</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7</id>
    <revision>
      <id>370</id>
      <parentid>334</parentid>
      <timestamp>2023-02-09T11:53:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anasfou</username>
        <id>5</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>370</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="13194" sha1="sx1fhm1ktq3r8e0qht6q4coy1ao6cvw" xml:space="preserve">== General questions ==

===Why so many standards?===
We can find explanations for why there are many and divers PT standards in both the functional scope involved, some specific technology needs, and of course history. 

==== Functional scope ====
Public transport encompasses many functions and many stakeholders; from the very small to very large; and operating in quite different modes, so naturally its data requirements span many different categories of data and many different use cases. '''Superficial discussion on the subject often tends to focus on a few specific categories of data that people are familiar with''' from their own use of using public transport, such as timetables, or real time departures, '''but they are of course only part of the wider picture.''' There are many other aspects to running a transport system, from '''managing the network infrastructure to planning and scheduling''', through to the '''collecting of fares,''' each needing the exchange of data. '''Informing the public with passenger information requires just a few categories out of many others.

==== Technology needs ====
An important point to note is that the different functions have an evolving temporal dimension – with different process taking place, before, during and after travel and this means that '''different technologies are needed to handle the real-time and dynamic aspects of a system as opposed to the static aspects.'''

'''Each different category of information thus has its own inherent submodel''' (for example for, stops, timetables, tariff structures, control, etc), and in most legacy formats has had different formats. Furthermore, the protocols that are efficient for the occasional bulk exchange of static or slow changing reference data are quite different from the protocols best suited for dynamic APIs, so we need two separate families of standards for gathering and for delivering data.

==== History ====
History is also instructive. If you look at what has been happening over the past 20 years, we see that in the late 1990’s we started out with numerous separate national formats as well as quite a few proprietary formats, mostly mode specific (predominately rail), not all very well documented and not all open or easy to extend. Over time, thanks to '''Transmodel, a gradual alignment of terminology and concepts''' allowed a common conceptual model to emerge in the early 2000’s, which in turn allowed '''a new generation of European national timetable standards to be developed''' that adopted the common terminology and took advantage of the reusable concepts that had been developed to simplify their representations. 

By the end of the decade, the various national timetable formats were close enough to consider creating a common XML format, to cover the network and timetables. This was done creating NeTEx, though there wasn’t actually a pressing business case for anyone to move to it and most countries concentrated on the uptake of their own still quite new national standards. On the API front , an early win was the development of the SIRI real-time API which was based on the German VDV 453 , harmonised to use the Transmodel terminology. This replaced a number of different national standards and is by now in widespread use in many European countries. APIs are of course easier and quicker to implement than bulk exchange formats  since they are views over existing data sets and data feeds and SIRI was . New data sets requiring a much bigger investment in database and tools to create data. 

No country has a standard format for exchanging multimodal fare data, yet alone one that can describe the sophisticated new types of electronic fare product made possible by smartcards and mobile devices. The Transmodel fare model was implemented as a further module of NeTEx to cover this gap. Although it is a distinct module   of NeTEx and has a large submodel of its own , it reuses existing NeTEx components for example stops, zones and lines and operators , where ever possible 

So even if there are still a confusingly number of PT standards out there, there are a great deal fewer than there would be if we hadn’t already made progress in standardisation.  

=== What is the difference between the different standards/formats? ===
Standardisations can take many flavours. You may have standardised designs, standards for protocols at different levels in the technology stack, standard formats for exchanging data, or even meta standards, that is standards for writing standards or for using a particular technology. Thus, '''different standards may apply at different levels of abstraction'''.

An important case in point is Transmodel itself: Transmodel isn’t a concrete format. It operates at a more abstract level, providing a common set of concepts and data structures with which to describe public transport entities and their relationships. As such it has a '''critical role as a unifying framework from which to develop concrete standards'''. But it means that when we consider a given format we are actually dealing with two standards at the same time. The good news is that Transmodel spans the entire domain – there is only one conceptual standard!

'''Concrete exchange formats and protocols necessarily have a smaller scope'''. And can be placed within the “bigger picture” A standard with relatively broad scope, such as NeTEx, actually needs to be carefully modularised so that it can be used selectively.

Considering the wider context of what we are really aiming at, that of '''gathering information from many sources to build useful applications''', we see that we '''need exchange formats not just for the “downstream” processes that deliver information to the passenger'''. But also, for the '''“upstream” processes that create and manage the data in the first place'''.

Although there are many common components, these '''upstream processes contain additional concepts that don’t need to be in the downstream data sets'''. For example when you are creating schedules you need to know the times over the links of a network in order to work out the timings that will ultimately  be shown the passenger in the finalised timetable. Downstream formats may use simplified views.  However with the massive grown in mobile devices and smart mobility apps, '''the long-term trend is to want more sophisticated function in the downstream systems too'''. It is there for '''attractive to have a richer format than can be used selectively in multiple different use cases.'''

== NeTEx related questions ==

=== Why to use NeTEx rather than the other similar standards? ===
In general, Transmodel family of standards, including NeTEx, are very strongly placed, in that they have a uniform, joined up, modular model that offer several key benefits:

==== On the technical front ====
* Ιt is a multimodal model built of reusable components that are rich enough to cover both upstream and downstream requirements. It provides a way to have a consistent description of all modes (including Vehicle Sharing and Pooling), and their relations (connection, bus station at train station, vehicle sharing station close to bus station, etc. etc.), where all other standards are unrelated silos.
* It is designed to be extensible. It has a model driven design that allows impact analysis to be done properly and has a modular implementation framework that can be further subtyped and otherwise added to.
* Τhe use of uniform components reduces complexity, giving headroom to add further capability.  
* It is designed to be customizable via profiles. With the definition of profiles NeTEx fit to national/local needs.
* Ιt is developed and checked by gathering the knowledge of experts from most EU countries, reaching high quality and consistency, overcoming the risk of shortcoming and mistakes that a locally defined data exchange protocol may encompasses.

==== On the business front ====
* The statutory requirements for NAPs provide a driving business case. Transmodel ecosystem is the regulated standard to be used in EU territory, based on the ITS Directive 2017/1926.
* The support of the European commission to develop supporting resources is helpful for reducing the barriers to entry and building critical mass.
* The development of open-source components and tools [ch3] further improve the economics.
* NeTEx can be standalone with no dependencies with SIRI, and vice versa but '''it is highly recommended to combine them.'''
* NeTEx can be applied in many different use cases that surpass the passenger information, like the operational data (AVMS), fares data, scheduling and production plan. Note: There is available training material where NeTEx functional scope and use cases are presented, [https://data4pt-project.eu/knowledge-database/training-material/ here].
For more details regarding the advantages and disavantages of NeTEx, please visit NeTEx website [http://netex-cen.eu/?page_id=185 here] 

=== What is the recommended process for developing or reviewing the national NeTEx profiles? ===
A profile is a subset of the standard defined to be used for a specific use case. For the countries that are now under the development of their first NeTEx national profile, we recommend staying as close as possible to the European Passenger Information Profile which includes the minimum information to be shared across countries for passenger information. More EU minimum profiles regarding Accessibility elements and Fares are now under development in the framework of DATA4PT project and will be published soon with the aim to support the countries in enhancing the type of the information that can be exchanged. 

==== Key steps to follow ====
1.    Use as basis the EU official minimum profiles. More specifically start with the EPI Profile and the relevant documentation. In the DATA4PT website you will find the graphic documentation, the XSD and an XML example regarding EPIP (&lt;nowiki&gt;https://data4pt-project.eu/knowledge-database/&lt;/nowiki&gt; stay). Moreover, we recommend you to watch the dedicated to EPIP webinar available [https://data4pt-project.eu/knowledge-database/training-material/ here]. 

2.    Clearly identify the national specific needs to be managed and added to the EPIP profile in order to fulfill country’s requirements. 

3.    Learn from others by analyzing their profiles and checking their examples. Currently, a list of countries with available national profiles is available [https://data4pt.org/wiki/NeTEX#National_profiles here]  . Examine which of the functionalities applied in other countries also fit to your needs and they can be adopted.

4.    Check the full NeTEx XSD and what elements/objects are included and reply to your needs. In case there is no available element, there is a possibility of providing the information under other elements. It is often possible to add more info to an element by using the keyList/KeyValue construction.

5.    Create examples and perform a first level validation by using XML validators such as Oxygen, SPY and other commercial tools. 

6.    Ask for feedback from [https://data4pt-project.eu/requests-requirements/ DATA4PT experts’ team]. 

Also keep in mind that conversion from an existing format is always possible, but if it looks like an easy first step, that may not be the easiest way to collect all the need information (needs or increasing very fast).

=== How widely NeTEx is used currently? ===
Given that many countries already have their own Transmodel based national standards for exchanging timetable data, there wasn’t initially much of a business case for most countries to start using NeTEx in earnest. So, in the first instance what we mainly saw was tools just adding NeTEx timetable export which is relatively simple to do if you are Transmodel based in the first place.  

A real business case is the '''example of Norway''' where they wanted to rebuild their entire national transport data infrastructure. The standard has been adopted with notable success and speed. The '''EU directives for National Access Points (NAPs)''' are of course changing this picture by creating a statutory requirement and you can already find initial NeTEx stop and timetable data sets on many countries National Access Points.

But there is still some way to go. A standard needs a whole ecology to be in widespread use so there is inevitably a bootstrapping problem, and for a new subdomain such as fare data. XML also  presents a challenge to some developers. 

Examples of countries that currently provide their data in NeTEx format are:

* [https://data.transportportal.no/datasets?lang=en Norway]
* [https://data.public.lu/en/datasets/ Luxembourg]
* [https://www.trafiklab.se/api/trafiklab-apis/netex-regional/ Sweden]
* [https://transport.data.gouv.fr/?locale=en France]
* [https://www.mobilitydata.gv.at/en Austria]
* [http://data.ndovloket.nl/ Netherlands]

Full list of European National Access Points regarding MMTIS Delegated Regulation 1926/2017 (action ‘a’) is available [https://ec.europa.eu/transport/sites/default/files/its-national-access-points.pdf here].
'</text>
      <sha1>sx1fhm1ktq3r8e0qht6q4coy1ao6cvw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>FAQ NeTEX</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>56</id>
    <revision>
      <id>721</id>
      <parentid>517</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-07-30T20:58:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>721</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="32340" sha1="5vx2nhazq5tpv5r5n3h49r41opqvoxj" xml:space="preserve">== How do you create C# classes from the NeTEx XSD? ==

It is possible to create C# classes in different ways.

There are many tools out there, but for instance, you could use the Microsoft xsd.exe tool or the mganss/XMLSchemaClassGenerator tool available on Github at https://github.com/mganss/XmlSchemaClassGenerator

Currently there are some issues if you try to use the official NeTEx XSD as a starting point with either of these tools.

However, the above-mentioned tools work fine if you use them together with an adapted set of XSD-files available from Data4PT. The file set is designed to be compatible with the official NeTEx XSD and to cover many important use cases. It does however not cover all use cases possible with the official schema. There is an interactive graphical presentation of the adapted and reduced XSD available at https://data4pt.org/NeTEx/GraphicKit/Documention_of_reduced_XSD.html

If you wish to try out this reduced XSD, you can download it at https://data4pt.org/NeTEx/GraphicKit/XSD_reduced.zip

The work steps if you are using the Microsoft tool are:

Get the zipped XSD. Extract the ZIP to a folder.
Make sure that you have a recent version of the xsd.exe. It is part of the .NET Framework Developer Pack and can be downloaded from https://dotnet.microsoft.com/download/dotnet-framework
Install the developer pack. The xsd.exe will be placed in a folder with a path similar to C:\Program Files (x86)\Microsoft SDKs\Windows\v10.0A\bin\NETFX 4.8 Tools
Open a command prompt in the same folder as where the NeTEx_publication_reduced-NoConstraint.xsd resides.
Execute the following command (you may have to adapt the path to xsd.exe): "C:\Program Files (x86)\Microsoft SDKs\Windows\v10.0A\bin\NETFX 4.8 Tools\xsd.exe"/c/language:C# gml_combo_v3_2_1_simplified.xsd NeTEx_publication_reduced-NoConstraint.xsd
The work steps if you are using the MGANSS tool are:

* Get the zipped XSD. Extract the ZIP to a folder.
* Download and extract the binary from https://github.com/mganss/XmlSchemaClassGenerator/releases to a separate folder e.g. C:\MGANSS.
* Open a command prompt in the same folder as where the NeTEx_publication_reduced-NoConstraint.xsd resides.
* Execute the following command (you may have to adapt the path to the exe):
C:\MGANSS\XmlSchemaClassGenerator.Console.exe NeTEx_publication_reduced-NoConstraint.xsd -n http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2=gml-v

--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 19:41, 19 May 2022 (CEST)

== Is it possible to get access to the fares/schedule data? ==

Yes, the part 3 of NeTEx is fully dedicated to fares and works for all modes of public transport (bus, trains, trams, flexible modes, etc.).

There is a set of white papers describing NeTEx (http://netex-cen.eu/?page_id=14) and one is dedicated to fares:
http://netex-cen.eu/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/10.NeTEx-Fare-WhitePaper_1.04.pdf

Fares can be quite big topic and people defining them have a lot of imagination. This resulted in NeTex Part 3 being quite big and it is strongly advised to use only a small subset of it which is relevant to your needs. This what we call a Profile. France, Nordic countries, and UK have a fares national profiles. Information about current national profiles is about existing profiles is available [https://data4pt.org/w/index.php?title=NeTEX#Published_profiles here]. A minimum European profile is currently under specification with the support of DATA4PT and it is planned to be delivered to CEN processes by end of June 2024. 

--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 10:28, 06 November 2023 (CEST)

== Is it correct to include the data category VehicleType in the TimetableFrame as in the NX-PI-01_LU_NAP_LINE_AVL-AVL-91_20210113.xml EPIP example file? ==

This example file is available for download under https://data4pt-project.eu/knowledge-database/guidelines/, it includes the data category VehicleType.
Yes, the European Passenger Information Profile, CEN/TS 16614-4:2020,(EPIP) states that the data category VehicleType can be provided in the TimetableFrame. See table 131 – TypeOfFrame: EU_PI_TIMETABLE in the documentation.

--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 19:50, 19 May 2022 (CEST)

== Are there other possibilities where to define the vehicle type? ==

Yes, the European Passenger Information Profile, CEN/TS 16614-4:2020,(EPIP) actually also allows, as an option, that the data category VehicleType is instead provided in the ResourceFrame. See table Table 127 – TypeOfFrame: EU_PI_COMMON in the documentation. This second option is now (2021-02-24) also supported in the set of XSD-files available for download from the project website.

--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 19:50, 19 May 2022 (CEST)

== How to manage translations with "MultilingualString" in NeTex? ==
There are a lot of MultilingualString in NeTEx. All implementions use them. It may be slightly different depending on the language (Java, C/C++, Ruby, Go, Python, etc.) and also on the use case (e.g. there are translations available to be used).

Furthermore, for translations, AlternativeTexts are expected to be used (they do contain MultilingualString but also some more information as presented in the following schema).

https://data4pt.org/w/images/2/2a/MultilingualString.png

Also note that an object can have multiple names (not translations but different possible naming): in such case AlternativeNames should be considered.

An xml example (EPIP example file), where MultilingualString attributes (lang) are used is available in the DATA4PT knowledge database.

To check your data sets, you may use EPIP adapted XML-schema. The graphic documentation of the EPIP NeTEx XSD, including MultilingualString description is available here .


Generally, NeTEx example files can be found in the main github repository ,  while also other databases with examples are available, (e.g. from ENTUR).

--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 19:57, 19 May 2022 (CEST)

== When I try to generate java classes, Ι have a duplication class error. Is it necessary to have those 2 types: vehicleJourneyStopAssignmentsInFrame_RelStructure and VehicleJourneyStopAssignmentsInFrame_RelStructure? ==

It should be only one branch vehicleJourneyStopAssignmentsInFrame_RelStructure. Maybe the second is in a "dead file". Please check https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx/blob/master/xsd/netex_part_2/part2_journeyTimes/netex_vehicleJourney_version.xsd).

In general, regarding java classes, you may check ENTUR recommendations available here https://github.com/entur/netex-java-model.

--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 20:03, 19 May 2022 (CEST)

== How to use "keylist" to express secondary identifiers for network? ==

The element ''keylist'' and child element ''KeyValue'' is the right way to add secondary identifiers for a network. The ''keylist'' element should be positioned before ''PrivateCode''. For example:
  &lt;Network version="any" changed="2022-06-10T09:30:36Z" id="FR1:Network:1045:LOC"&gt;
     &lt;keyList&gt;
       &lt;KeyValue typeOfKey="ALTERNATE_IDENTIFIER"&gt;
         &lt;Key&gt;NETWORK_SAE&lt;/Key&gt;
         &lt;Value&gt;456&lt;/Value&gt;
       &lt;/KeyValue&gt;
     &lt;/keyList&gt;
     &lt;PrivateCode&gt;123&lt;/PrivateCode&gt;
  &lt;/Network&gt;

--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 18:47, 11 June 2022 (CEST)

== Is there a way to express in NeTEx and/or SIRI that the information of provided occupancy level of a public transport vehicle is based on a prognosis (e.g. historical data) or real-time measured data? ==

SIRI VM (vehicle monitoring service) and SIRI SM (stop monitoring) already today allow a simple enumeration describing the general Occupancy level for a monitored Vehicle Journey.
In the coming SIRI version (currently under voting process):
- the enumeration value set will be extended and additional values added. Some additional constructions on Call level will also be added.
- SIRI Estimated Timetable (ET) will be extended  with the possibility to exchange passenger count and occupancy information per Call. This will include recorded information as well as estimated values for coming Calls.
The XSD itself is already fully finalised and usable from here https://github.com/SIRI-CEN/SIRI 

Also, you can find a very relevant document about " Vehicle Occupancy Data" from RTIG (UK trade body for public transport technology stakeholders) here : https://www.rtig.org.uk/system/files/documents/RTIGT039-1.1%20Providing%20Vehicle%20Occupancy%20Data%20-%20Data%20Interfaces.pdf
It includes detailed references to SIRI and NeTEx data structures :
- The NeTEx format includes PassengerCapacity as part of the VehicleType and has a structure that allows for detail - including seated and standing capacities, to be handled
- The Occupancy field in SIRI is one of the optional properties of ProgressInfo of a MonitoredVehicleJourney. This element can be used in both SIRI-SM and SIRI-VM services.
- There is, in addition, an Occupancy field in the EstimatedCall structure of the SIRI-ET service. If this is populated it represents a predicted passenger load. If the corresponding field is filled in a MonitoredVehicleJourney, this should be used in preference - as it reflects the actual current passenger occupancy value.

--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 12:40, 03 August 2022 (CEST)

== How different levels of stops of complex stations are expressed in NeTEx EPIP? ==

To describe different levels of stops in complex stations, the XSD is adapted as follows: 

&lt;xsd:complexType name="levels_RelStructure"&gt;
    &lt;xsd:sequence&gt;
        &lt;xsd:element ref="Level" maxOccurs="unbounded"/&gt;
    &lt;/xsd:sequence&gt;
    &lt;xsd:attributeGroup ref="ModificationSetAttributeGroup"/&gt;
&lt;/xsd:complexType&gt; 

The updated XSD is available https://data4pt.org/w/index.php?title=NeTEX#NeTEx_EPIP.
--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 13:32, 3 August 2022 (CEST)

== How to differentiate a basic JourneyPattern from one that takes into account re-routings due to planned deviations? ==

For planned deviations, another version of JourneyPattern needs to be described having different validity conditions than the regular JourneyPattern. For deviations that occur the same day of the operation, SIRI Estimated Timetable (ET) can be used, and for deviations known some days before the operational day, SIRI Production Timetable (PT) can be used.

Moreover, there is today no element in the XSD that states if a JourneyPattern is "normal" or "diversion".
This means that you would probably need to analyse the timetable over a longer period of time and compare how often different JourneyPatterns (or versions of a certain JourneyPattern) are actually used on a certain Direction to find which is the "normal" one.

--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 19:16, 9 September 2022 (CEST)

== Where can I find the UML model for NeTEX? ==

The UML of NeTEx is available https://www.netex-cen.eu/model/conceptual/part1/index.htm. NeTEx is based on data model Transmodel, of which the UML is available in Enterprise Architect file https://www.transmodel-cen.eu/model/. This version corresponds to the CEN v6.0 release c2018, with revisions from 2021. For more information regarding the data model (Transmodel) please check here https://www.transmodel-cen.eu/downloads/. Updates on the Transmodel UML are expected in the coming period.

--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 16:08, 22 September 2022 (CEST)

== Where can I find information about how and when NeTEx is going to be able to store data about: taxi services, rent of vehicles (with or without driver), parking areas (the classical one, for private cars etc.), low emission zones in cities?  ==

TRANSMODEL Part 10 and NeTEx Part 5 (Alternative Modes API) are relevant to the referred functional scope except of low emission zones. In particular, NeTEx Part 5, covers all alternative modes: Vehicle Sharing (any kind of vehicle, car, bike, scooter etc.), Vehicle Pooling (any kind of vehicle, car, van etc.), Transport Network Companies, Renting, Taxis. 

NeTEx also includes mobilityServiceConstraintZones that can be applied to any public transport and new mode services and be a restriction for certain types of vehicles. However this needs to be connected to some services, since NeTEx and Transmodel are not describing the private vehicle use (except for carpooling where there is a public offer on the private vehicle). So, there is no explicit description of Low Emission Zones, where the limitation is triggered by a pollution level. Possible enhancement can be considered.

NeTEx Part 5 (CEN/TS 16614-5) is complementary to the previous parts (1/2/3/4). It is fully aligned with the new Transmodel Part 10, being the underlaying data model.
Transmodel extension published as CEN TS 17413:2019. The conversion of CEN TS 17413:2019 into an EN is going to be the Transmodel -Part 10. General information about NeTEx Part 5 is available here http://netex-cen.eu/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/NeTEx-extension-for-New-Modes-Detailed-Scope-v04.pdf. The specifications are also now published by CEN.

Besides the CEN documentation, the users (IT suppliers/operators,  in general developers etc.) can have access to the technical artefacts (XSD) through the publicly available repository in GitHub (check https://data4pt.org/w/index.php?title=NeTEX#NeTEx_Part_5_for_New_Modes). In addition, there is an available mapping-comparison with GBFS, the bike sharing data format from Mobility Data https://data4pt.org/w/index.php?title=NeTEX#Canonical_mapping_with_GBFS.

Since NeTEx is about scheduled data (including location of parking places, capacity etc.), is complemented by SIRI for realtime data. Therefore, SIRI has also been extended (recently voted) to cover new modes (vehicles availability, parking places availability etc.). This extension is in SIRI Part 4 (Facility Monitoring). 
In particular for parking, there is a comprehensive description in NeTEx. France for example has already a dedicated profile for parking – the documentation in french is available here http://www.normes-donnees-tc.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/NF_Profil-NeTEx-pour-les-ParkingsF-v1.2a.pdf ). 

--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 16:28, 22 September 2022 (CEST)

== How to manage codespaces in NeTEx where unique identifiers are needed? ==

In NeTEx a rule to code IDs is included to ease uniqueness (Europe wide) and stability of IDs. 


[[File:1.jpg|thumb]]

For example in Italy, they applied this rule, using NUTS code for country-code and local-code.

&lt;ServiceCalendarFrame id="epd:IT:ITC1:ServiceCalendarFrame_EU_PI_CALENDAR:scf" version="any"&gt;
&lt;TypeOfFrameRef versionRef="any" ref="epip:EU_PI_CALENDAR"/&gt;
&lt;ServiceCalendar id="IT:ITC1:ServiceCalendar:C01" version="any"&gt;
&lt;dayTypes&gt;
&lt;DayType id="IT:ITC1:DayType:5:dt:A" version="any"&gt;

Any other rule can be accepted provided that IDs are unique and stable. Using operator's code inside an ID is not suggested as the Operator can change. With the NeTEx recommended rule, even if the Operator changes, the ID will have to remain the same, ignoring that change. Also the Operator code may not be a good choice for the uniqueness of shared lines or shared stops.

--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 10:04, 05 October 2022 (CEST)


== How to describe two similar stops sequences when the one has a boarding and alighting information and the other has not? ==

One ROUTE is enough, it can cover two different JOURNEY PATTERNS if the vehicle will traverse the same physical path in both cases. The relation between ROUTE POINT and SCHEDULED STOP POINT is formally through projection.


--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 11:12, 2 November 2022 (CET)

== Should "RouteLink" have a unique identifier? ==

Each unique RouteLink should have a unique identifier (id-attribute). 
Note that a RouteLink over time may be altered and still retain its original identifier, but  each modification should have a different version-attribute.

At the same time it is OK to refer to the same RouteLink in relation to different Lines, if those Lines include a shared physical path for some part of the respective routes. This applies also if the Lines are provided in separate files.

--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 15:44, 12 January 2023 (CET)

== What is the difference between stopAreas, Quays, stopPlaces? ==


A STOP AREA is "A group of SCHEDULED STOP POINTs close to each other." so it definitely does not correspond to the quays and stopPlaces of the IFOPT base.

Having a scheduledStopPoint belonging a a single journeyPattern, however this does go via the StopPointInJourneyPattern which is allowing multiple reuse of the same scheduledStopPoint. A scheduledStopPoint can be assigned to StopPlace or Quays thanks to the PassengerStopAssignment.
[[File:Stop assignment model.png|thumb]]













--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 11:50, 3 May 2023 (CET)
== How to model a transport ticket that costs 6 euros on the 1st day and 3 euros for each additional day? ==

This is a typical case of pricing of a SALES OFFER PACKAGEs: several such packages may exist composed of 1, 2,…n elements and a specific price is provided according to the number of the SALES OFFER PACKAGE ELEMENTS in the SALES OFFER PACKAGE.

So for this particular example:
The PRICE of the SALES OFFER PACKAGE composed of one SALES OFFER PACKAGE ELEMENT is 6 euros.
The price of the SALES OFFER PACKAGE composed of 2…n SALES OFFER PACKAGE ELEMENTs is 6 + (n-1)*3 euros.

You may consider a PREASSIGNED FARE PRODUCT (e.g. a day pass) which is provided by one or more SALES OFFER PACKAGE ELEMENTs. Access rights may correspond to a PREASSIGNED FARE PRODUCT but also other types of access right might be granted by a SALES OFFER PACKAGE ELEMENT.

Moreover, the definition of TimeIntervals  is related to the description of the time-related fare structure elements  (for example the use of the network during 1 hour would represent a SALES OFFER PACKAGE ELEMENT A - 1 hour pass, the use of the network during 5 hours represent a SALES OFFER PACKAGE ELEMENT B - 5 hours pass). In the present example, the fare structure elements are identical (use of the network during one day several times). So only the pricing differs according to the number of products purchased. TimeInterval will be rather suitable to the pricing of a single trip (DayOffset are only there because some long distance trips can exceed the day).

[[File:Stop assignment model.png|thumb]]













--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 11:13, 1 September 2023 (CET)
== How to model "hail and ride" section? ==
Hail and ride usually is modelled by using a FlexibleStopPlace that can refer to HailAndRide areas as shown in the UML diagrams below. Hail and Ride is described in CEN TS 16614-1. Examples can be found in [https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx/tree/master/examples NeTEx-CEN GitHub] like this [https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx/blob/master/examples/functions/timetable/Netex_01.4_Bus_SimpleTimetable_WithConnection.xml one].

[[File:FlexibleStopPlace with HailandRideArea.png|thumb|UML diagram of FlexibleStopPlace with HailAndRide]]


[[File:HailAndRide.png|thumb|364x364px]]















--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 16:40, 17 October 2023 (CET)

== How to start implementing NeTEx Part 5 for new modes (vehicle sharing, rental, taxis etc.)? ==
Simple steps for new users/implementers of NeTEx Part 5:  

1) Watch the introduction webinar for NeTEx Part 5, available on [https://data4pt-project.eu/knowledge-database/training-material/ DATA4PT website] under the title “DATA4PT webinar 24 November 2022: NeTEx and SIRI standards for new modes” (direct link to the [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F_lK1mfKgbk video] and presentation of the [https://data4pt-project.eu/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/DATA4PT-NeTEx-validation-tool-webinar_Presentation.pdf webinar]). 

2) Read the pdf – official CEN documentation CEN/TS 16614-5 (where also some examples are given). The document can be bought from any national standardization body. 

3) Use XML editor (there are commercial tools or free tools - a short list is available by [https://data4pt.org/w/index.php?title=NeTEX#Software_.26_tools_.F0.9F.A7.B0 DATA4PT wiki]), to check the [https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx/tree/master/xsd/netex_part_5 XSD for Part 5]  and check the [https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx/tree/master/examples/functions/newModes examples] from [https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx/tree/master Github NeTEx repository]. 

4) Create your own .xml examples based on the XSD and the examples available in GitHub. If the user has no technical background, then IT tool provider is needed to support him/her following the same steps. A general list of tools is available in [https://data4pt.org/w/index.php?title=NeTEX#Software_.26_tools_.F0.9F.A7.B0 DATA4PT wiki.]    

5) Validate the example with the XML editor and the Greenlight validator. The latter is the tool that provides feedback both on errors that concern the NeTEx XSD but also the content (plausibility checks). 

6) Use the [https://data4pt-project.eu/requests-requirements/ DATA4PT helpdesk] for more technical guidance.      

Finally, a useful material for small operators that they use already GBFS is:

-the canonical mapping between GBFS and NeTEx/SIRI to get their head around the fields/attributes they need at a quick glance

- the .xml example that is GBFS-based from the NeTEx GitHub repo.

Relevant material is available [https://data4pt.org/w/index.php?title=NeTEX#NeTEx_part_5_for_.F0.9F.86.95_modes here]


--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 10:45, 6 November 2023 (CET)



== How to implement DayTypeAssignment in NeTEx? Using OperatingPeriodRef or UicOperatingPeriodRef? ==

Both "OperatingPeriodRef" and "UicOperatingPeriodRef" are in the same substitutionGroup named OperatingPeriods, therefore both options may be used without impacting the interoperability of the file. UicOperatingPeriodRef is probably cleaner to reference a UicOperatingPeriod.In NeTEx EPIP (European Passenger Information Profile) UicOperatingPeriod is mandatory (providing the ValidDayBits is mandatory).
[[File:Image.png|thumb]]




--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 12:18, 16 February 2024 (CET)

== Does a scheduledStopPoint ID need to be unique per public transport Line?  ==

A scheduledStopPoint ID does not need to be unique per Line.
In situations where several Lines use the exact same stop point they may refer to this same stop point using the same scheduledStopPoint ID. If there is a unique ID for the exact same stop that can be used globally it is also ideal from interoperability point of view. 

More precisely, based on NeTEx terminology, a LINE is defined as "A group of ROUTEs which is generally known to the public by a similar name or number."
A ROUTE is defined as "An ordered list of located POINTs defining one single path through the road (or rail) network. A ROUTE may pass through the same POINT more than once."
JOURNEY PATTERN, defined as "An ordered list of SCHEDULED STOP POINTs and TIMING POINTs on a single ROUTE, describing the pattern of working for public transport vehicles. A JOURNEY PATTERN may pass through the same POINT more than once. The first point of a JOURNEY PATTERN is the origin. The last point is the destination."

In order not to make confusion, when parsing the XML input, the data user needs to sufficiently preserving awareness of the context in which the scheduledStopPoint ID is being used. With a correct awareness of the context, the ID can be augmented, for example via a composite ID made up of Line plus stop IDs. This would make different occurrences of the same stop have different IDs, without breaking the NeTEx rules. 



--[[User:Anasfou|DATA4PT Team]] ([[User talk:Anasfou|talk]]) 17:38, 25 March 2024 (CET)

== Can NeTEx handle frequency-based services? ==
Frequency based serves are typically specified as operating at a given interval, rather than particular times. From a passenger point of view multiple journeys will typically be presented as a single journey running at an approximate interval, for example “every six to 10 minutes”. NeTEx uses TEMPLATE VEHICLE journeys to describe such journeys. From an operational point of view there will still need to be specific service journeys scheduled to fulfil the required frequency of service and NeTEx can also include these to support real time journeys. 

== Can I have different journey timings for different times of day? ==
Part 2 of NeTEx includes reusable components for constructing timetables of journeys from reusable components, NeTEx separates the concerns of where the timing of a PT route takes place (The TIMING PATTERN made up of TIMING POINTs and TIMING LINKs) from the actual timing values (which are held separately as RUN TIMEs and WAIT TIMEs). Different sets of timing values belong to different TIME DEMAND TYPEs (Peak, off peak, late night, etc) can be used with the same TIMING PATTERN to generate accurate timetables for journeys at different times of day.

== Can NeTEx describe zone-based fares? ==
NeTEx can be used to describe zone-based fare systems of any topology ranging from a simple patchwork (adjacent zones) to the complex, (honeycomb, doughnut) etc). The TARIFF ZONE allows zones to be associated with stops and stations. Mixed zonal and stage systems are also possible. Fare pricing may be a flat fare system per zone, or   zone to zone using a (DISTANCE MATRIX ELEMENT), or be differentially priced for particular sequences of zones (using FARE STRUCTURE ELEMENTs in SEQUENCE). 

== Can I restrict certain products to certain classes of user? ==
Among the many different usage conditions that can be specified for NeTEx fare products are restrictions on the type of user – child, senior, student, disabled, etc using a USER PROFILE that may be given precise eligibility criteria (e.g. on age, membership, domicile, etc). A GROUP PROFILE allows the number and makeup of groups to be specified; it can also be used to specify companion criteria for disabled users and other special cases. 

== Can I specify time-based constraints on travel? ==
Some fare products only allow travel at particular times – such constraints can be expressed using USAGE PARAMETERs.  Others only allow travel for a particular duration; FARE STRUCTURE ELEMENTs with TIME STUCTURE FACTORs can be used to describe the different durations. Furthermore, sometimes journey time is related to journey length, so for example a longer time is allowed for a two-zone trip than a one zone trip; all this can be precisely specified in NeTEx. 

Temporal conditions may also apply to the purchase or refund of tickets, likewise, expressed as USAGE PARAMETERs attached to fare products. 

As well as the routine examples given above, NeTEx can also handle more complex cases.  For example, in the periphery of a large city, off peak times may start at different times in each station since by the time a journey to the centre starting from the station ends, the peak period will have ended. 

== Does NeTEx support dynamic/yield managed pricing? ==
For long-distance travel, especially on-rail, there is increasing use of yield managed fares with dynamic pricing, provided by web services. Note that such applications increase rather than decrease the need for standards such as NeTEx as such applications nonetheless require a machine-readable definition of the access rights fare structure and usage conditions that apply to the products for which prices are supplied. Furthermore, the search parameters used to find the best fare for a user (such as age, possession of rail cards, fulfilment method etc) need to correspond to the properties of the fare product. The NeTEx Part3 specification and UML model includes an annex showing a sample fare query which shows all the NeTEx model elements relevant for constructing a Fare API. 

== Can NeTEx define products for modern e-card based ticketing? ==
Yes. Electronic payment cards such as OV Chipkart (NL), Oyster (London region), Navigo (Paris region) Sube T (Madrid), BIP Card (Turin) are becoming increasingly common and etc transport operators are able to devise increasingly sophisticate products. For example,, Oyster has fares that adjust according to consumption, capping the cost of trips made in a day to that of a day pass. NeTEx is able to describe the fare structures and scope and conditions for such complex products, as well as to supporting a record of consumption for account-based products. (A NeTEx SALES TRANSACTION records an individual PRODUCT SALE). 

As products on cards are physical invisible to the user, the ability to create user readable representations become increasingly important – such applications require a machine-readable format with corresponding human readable rendering, such as is available through NeTEx. 

== Does NeTEx support Flexible and Demand Responsive Travel? ==
Yes, unlike classical route and timetable standards, NeTEx is also designed to support FTS (Flexible Transport Service) and DRT (Demand Responsive Transport). DRT and FTS often cover similar services; FTS being more generic since flexibility may not be directly linked to the demand, but may be related to some operating needs or cost optimisations. 

The flexibility can be applied to the line, route and stop structure (areas, corridors, hail and ride, etc.) or to their scheduling (dynamic and/or demand responsive passing times, with all necessary booking arrangements and contact details). 

== Can I create applications to run in different national Languages? ==
Yes, NeTEx includes full support for internationalisation. All text elements may be created in multiple languages so that place names and other names and descriptions can be provided in one or more languages. Other aspects important for multiregional use are parameterized such as time zones, currency, etc. and the Calendar functions allow conditions based on different national holidays to be described. 

== Can I have different versions of data for the same element extant at the same time? ==
Yes, every NeTEx data element can be versioned, and multiple versions can coexist. Coherent sets of data are assembled for exchange using a ‘version frame’, which itself has a version and knows the version of the elements in it. There are specific types of version frame for different types of data that are commonly exchanged together (SERVICE, TIMETABLE, FARE etc). 

== Can I create Network maps with NeTEx? ==
Yes, one of the additional capabilities of NeTEx is the ability to define and exchange the full topology of a network as presented in simplified view to a user (often with presentational attributes such as colour), with non-directional network segments, loops etc, while also retaining a projection onto the actual underlying stops and route. This allows automatic creation of interactive map applications. 

* The LINE element names the line and sets basic properties 

* The LINE NETWORK and LINE SECTION elements can be used to describe the topology 

* The ROUTE, ROUTELINK, and ROUTE POINT elements can be used to define the directional elements of the underlying line 

* The SCHEDULED STOP POINT can be used to define the stops of a line. 

All these objects can have their own geographic positions and geometry or/and be projected onto a custom drawn map using a SCHEMATIC MAP element. 

== I have my own classification for Stops/ Lines / etc. Can NeTEx handle this? ==
Yes, NeTEx allows arbitrary user defined code classifications for elements using the TYPE OF STOP, TYPE OF LINE and other ‘Type of Entity’ elements that. In addition, NeTEx, to encourage standardised use, also provides fixed enumerations of many commonly found classifications of specific elements, including types of equipment, on-board facilities, etc. The ‘Key Value’ extension mechanism allows Also allows additional user defined attributes to be added, which can include classifier.</text>
      <sha1>5vx2nhazq5tpv5r5n3h49r41opqvoxj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>FAQ NeTEx</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>48</id>
    <revision>
      <id>337</id>
      <timestamp>2023-02-07T16:23:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Created blank page</comment>
      <origin>337</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="0" sha1="phoiac9h4m842xq45sp7s6u21eteeq1" xml:space="preserve" />
      <sha1>phoiac9h4m842xq45sp7s6u21eteeq1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>FAQ SIRI</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>47</id>
    <revision>
      <id>470</id>
      <parentid>469</parentid>
      <timestamp>2023-11-03T14:36:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anasfou</username>
        <id>5</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* How to best model the logic "AND" of GTFS- RT in SIRI SX (Situation Exchange)? */</comment>
      <origin>470</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1975" sha1="bfnhbzhrpe73b3pyzdfi1egkehppdld" xml:space="preserve">== How to best model the logic "AND" of GTFS- RT in SIRI SX (Situation Exchange)? ==
SIRI technical standard offers to also have publications of diversified information (with the possibility of having variants depending on the communication channels and also their location), in addition to allowing the management of multiple consequences. For example when referring to a line, we do not inform the same way upstream and downstream of the disturbance. 

In the following example of GTFS'RT message, 

"informed_entity": [
{
"route_id": "13",
"stop_id": "quay11"
},
{
"route_id": "13",
"stop_id": "quay12"
}
], where for route 13 and 2 platforms 11 and 12 are impacted, 

the "informed_entity" of GTFS-RT a priori concerns PublishingActions in SIRI which via PublishAtScope-&gt;Affects-&gt;StopPoints makes it possible to point as well the stops concerned (with the possibility of specifying the Quay number, see StopPointType).

The PublishingActions are described in SIRI Situation Exchange (Part 5 - CEN/TS 15531-5:2022) and is also included in the EU profile.

== Is it possible to use JSON/REST interface instead of XML for NeTEx and SIRI data exchange? ==
In general, JSON should be in addition to XML, so it means you need anyway XML. JSON is working in different way than XML. If the data to exchange is huge, this fact can break JSON. For large files is better to use XML that parses only the part you want to access, line per line and within a time window.  

Regarding SIRI, IDFM (Ile de France Mobilité -Authority from Paris Area) provides a REST/JSON access point by simply converting the original XML to JSON. Others are also doing REST but still using the XML data (REST does not imply JSON, and a lot of REST services are XML based). 

It is also recommended to check SIRI Part 2 for further insights, as well as the following report http://www.normes-donnees-tc.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Proposition-Profil-SIRI-Lite-initial-v1-2.pdf. (available in French).</text>
      <sha1>bfnhbzhrpe73b3pyzdfi1egkehppdld</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>FAQ Transmodel</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46</id>
    <revision>
      <id>372</id>
      <parentid>371</parentid>
      <timestamp>2023-02-10T12:51:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Is it modeled right? */</comment>
      <origin>372</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8038" sha1="4cf3wjwggmyjqp3jz85d2ssltdypees" xml:space="preserve">
== Conceptual modelling – separating concerns &amp; identifying analogies ==

=== ORGANISATION DAY TYPE ===

==== '''What is it really used for and why is it modeled so complex?''' ====
Transmodel provides the concept of DAY TYPE defined as a type of day characterised by one or more properties which affect public transport operation. For example: weekday in school holidays. 

This concept is intended to be used by organisations (in particular operators) in charge of the planning of public transport services.

Transmodel provides the following types of organisations:

[[File:TMOrgTypes.png]]

A TRANSPORT ORGNISATION is providing transport services related to particular modes of operation.

Other types of organisations exist, in particular '''SERVICED ORGANISATIONs''' which are public or private organisations '''for which public transport services are provided''' on specific days, e.g. a school, university or works. 

ORGANISATION DAY TYPE is a DAY TYPE that is defined '''in terms of operation or not operation''' of a referenced SERVICED ORGANISATION (specific DAY TYPE).

This concept is used to describe a reality proper to an organisation '''serviced by public transport.''' 

Example:  

PT services are defined for DAY TYPES Monday, Tuesday, Wedenesday, Thursday, Friday. Some schools in France are closed on Wedensdays, so the service is not required on Wednesdays. 

In this case we have ORGANISATION DAY TYPEs: 

·       Monday-Tuesday-Thursday-Friday characterised by 'isServiceDay' = true  and 

·       Wednesday charactrised by ' isServiceDay '= false.  

The additional attribute 'isServiceDay' is present in NeTEx.

===INDIVIDUAL PASSENGER INFO===

===='''Why is INDIVIDUAL PASSENGER INFO not just a structure within INDIVIDUAL TRAVELLER?'''====
An INDIVIDUAL TRAVELLER may be a driver (e.g. in car pooling) '''or''' a passenger . 

Therefore we have both: INDIVIDUAL PASSENGER INFO and VEHICLE POOLING DRIVER INFO.

[[File:Individual Traveller and driver model 1.png]]

Here, the roles of an INDIVIDUAL TRAVELLER are separated  and the attributes reflect '''the main requirements/characteristics related to each role.'''

NB: the list of attributes reflects the MAIN characteristics allowing to describe the semantics of a concept – NeTEx provides in may cases some more properties.

===VEHICLE MEETING LINK===

===='''Some conceptual explanation would be nice (and better description).'''====
Transmodel provides data structures for conventional modes of operation. Some basic concepts are VEHICLE JOURNEY, SERVICE PATTERN, SCHEDULED STOP POINT, SERVICE LINK, etc

As regards alternative mode of operation, similar concepts do exist:

·      The SINGLE JOURNEY hast to be seen at the same functional  level as a VEHICLE JOURNEY, but without the associated DAY TYPE/CALENDAR (only associated to a OPERTING DAY).

·      The SINGLE JOURNEY PATH is at the same level as the SERVICE PATTERN: the SERVICE PATTERN is a sequence of  SCHEDULED STOP POINT, and the SINGLE JOURNEY PATH is a sequence of VEHICLE MEETING POINTS.

·      Both SINGLE JOURNEY PATH and SERVICE PATTERN are related to a schematic itinerary:  a ROUTE.

·      The SERVICE LINK (link between tso SCHEDLED STOP POINTS) has to be seen at the same functional level as a VEHICLE MEETING LINK (link between two VEHICLE MEETING POINTs). 

[[File:NM_Vehicle_Meeting_Point.png|alt=|border]]

The functional similarity of the VEHICLE MEETING LINK with a SERVICE LINK for a CONVENTIONAL MODE OF OPERATION means:  '''it is a link along which no pick-up/drop-off operation can take place.'''

===VEHICLE MEETING POINT IN PATH===

====Is it modeled right?====
[[File:SERVICE_PATTERN_1.png|alt=|border]]

====POINT IN SERVICE PATTERN can also be each intermediate point, which is not a VEHICLE MEETING POINT. It is not 2 but an infinite amount of those in the SINGLE JOURNEY according to the diagram. ====

SINGLE JOURNEY PATH is an ordered list of '''VEHICLE MEETING POINTs''' on a single ROUTE, describing the pattern of working for an ALTERNATIVE MODE service.

A SINGLE JOURNEY PATH may pass through the same POINT more than once. The first point of a SINGLE JOURNEY PATH is the origin. The last point is the destination.

'''VEHICLE MEETING POINT IN PATH is a VEHICLE MEETING POINT with an order''' on the SINGLE JOURNEY PATH.

Two or more (2..* ) '''VEHICLE MEETING POINTs describe a''' SINGLE JOURNEY PATH.

==Modelling SITE, PARKING, their components vs. EQUIPMENT==

===PARKING &amp; PARKING ENTRANCE FOR VEHICLE ===

===='''The barrier type of a PARKING would be important as well. Also how the payment is to be done. Should this be modelled? The barrier type (at ENTRANCE) should be mentioned. Shouldn't it?'''====
The ENTRANCE is a physical object (with dimensions) providing entrance/exit to/from a SITE (here PARKING) which may be marked by a barrier (or a door). 

A barrier/door is an equipment. So the type of barrier would be related to the concept of 'Barrier' (non present in Transmodel) '''and not the the concept of entrance''' (which is not considered an equipment).

=== PARKING EXIT ===
'''Is there a reason that PARKING EXIT was not modelled?'''

PARKING is a SITE with an ENTRANCE defined as follows: a physical '''entrance or exit to/from a SITE'''. May be '''''(marked by)''''' a door, barrier, gate or other recognizable point of access.

=== PARKING RENTAL STATUS ===

==== '''A parking for bike/e-bike: Should it be modeled as two PARKING?''' ====
If it is a single parking, no: if it’s 2 zone in a single PARKING, then just define 2 PARKING AREAS, if they share the same PARKING AREA then just put both '''eCycle''' and '''cycle''' in '''ParkingVehicleTypes''' (in NeTEx).

=== TAXI STAND ===

==== '''How to model simple drop-off points for TAXI? Only allowed to get people out of the taxi? Should perhaps mentioned, if this is a simple VEHICLE MEETING POINT.''' ====
When a place is fully or partially dedicated to taxi pick-up &amp; drop-off, the best is to use a '''TAXI STAND''' (that can be stand alone on included in a wider site, like a STOP PLACE or a POINT OF INTEREST). 

When it comes to be an «unformal» pick-up &amp; drop-off point, then '''VEHICLE MEETING POINT''' ist he best way to go. Through the VEHICLE MEETING POINT ASSIGNMENT, it can be assigned to any SITE COMPONENT, or just freely defiend with geographic coordinates.

== Fares &amp; ticketing ==

=== TICKET SCOPE ===

==== '''I do not understand the definition. What ist he element for?''' ====
TICKET SCOPE is the broad geographic validity if the ticket: local, national, international.

It describes service restrictions, for example for ticket vending machines which may be dedicated to a type of ticket.

=== TOUCH ON/OFF TRANSACTIONS ===

==== '''Where I could find the "touch on" and "touch off" transactions component in the Transmodel? Are there captured in Transmodel?''' ====
In Transmodel, there are ticketing components that are modelled such as FM FE Passenger Travel Match Event MODEL. 

The diagram below includes, for instance, 

*PASSENGER CHECK IN ENTRY (recording PASSENGER CHECK IN EVENT) and
*PASSENGER CHECK OUT ENTRY (recording PASSENGER CHECK OUT EVENT).

[[File:TM3-2.png|1080px]]

This UML diagram is included in Transmodel Part 5 which deals with Fare management. 

It represents several events which are triggering the corresponding log entries. 


NB. for describing the technical behaviour of a relevant device (for example the needed duration of the contact between the card and the equipment, the maximum distance between them, etc.), the scope is probably related to the smart card standards.

== Equipment ==

=== VEHICLE CHARGING EQUIPMENT ===

==== '''Description of FreeCharging unclear if the Equipment is free to be used or free of charge. Perhaps also an attribute for working/out of service?''' ====
FreeRecharging = free of charge. 

NB. For any Equipment, NeTEx provides an attribute 'OutOfService' (but which does not describe the status variations of the equipment in real time…)</text>
      <sha1>4cf3wjwggmyjqp3jz85d2ssltdypees</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>France</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>88</id>
    <revision>
      <id>621</id>
      <parentid>610</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-10-08T12:54:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Admin moved page [[Draft:France]] to [[France]]</comment>
      <origin>610</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4486" sha1="nvqj1ralwdrovn74d3wn6ltjc33pgls" xml:space="preserve">== Overview in the National Level ==

=== Current Situation ===
Many datasets based on NeTEx and SIRI standard are available in [https://transport.data.gouv.fr/?locale=en French National Access Point] .
* '''Mass transit''': 114 datasets in NeTEx – French Profile format are available (excluding tariff and accessibility data) out of 421 total mass transit datasets.
* '''Mass transit (Real-time)''': 25 SIRI datasets are available compared to 159 GTFS-RT datasets.
* '''Pedestrian accessibility''': 2 datasets in NeTEx – French Profile format have been provided.

=== Upcoming Developments ===
For several months, towns and regions have been collecting accessibility-related data and plan to publish it in NeTEx – French Profile. A decree issued in May has strengthened the collection of this data.

In connection with the single-ticketing experiment, the French NAP team is assisting data producers, particularly in 2 regions, in providing their tariff data in NeTEx – French Profile.

More NeTEx and SIRI mass transit datasets are expected to be published in the coming months, as stakeholders are now ready to produce them. The French NAP team is actively supporting these efforts.

A French Profile for new mobility modes (such as free-floating services) is currently in development, although the release date is still unknown.

The French NAP is also working on implementing a NeTEx validation tool to help providers comply with the standard.

== Use cases ==

=== Description ===
More information regarding the implementation of public transport standards can be found at the following link: [https://transport.data.gouv.fr/stats#public-transport-format Public Transport Format Statistics]. This includes data from regions such as '''Nouvelle-Aquitaine''', '''Pays de la Loire''', and '''Île-de-France'''.

In '''Paris''' and some surrounding towns, NeTEx accessibility datasets have been provided through an experimental project that involved converting data from OpenStreetMap into the NeTEx format. Further details on this initiative can be found here: [https://transport.data.gouv.fr/datasets?q=jungle+bus Jungle Bus Datasets].

European regulations require transport authorities to provide datasets in the NeTEx format. As a result, an increasing number of local authorities and digital service providers recognize the utility of this standard, especially for establishing a multimodal information system. French law mandates that these multimodal systems must cover every region in the country.

Despite the growing acceptance of NeTEx, many transport authorities and private transport operators find the standard to be overly complex. While some digital service providers have mastered certain aspects of NeTEx, the intricate nature of the standard presents challenges for broader adoption.

To support the transition, the French Ministry of Transport has invested in developing specific tools that assist producers in collecting accessibility data and publishing it in the NeTEx format. This financial backing aims to simplify the process and encourage compliance with the standard among local authorities.

=== Architecture ===
The implementation of public transport standards follows the guidelines set forth in the French Profile, which can be accessed [https://normes.transport.data.gouv.fr/ here]. This profile is compatible with the EPIP (Échange de données pour l'Information et la Planification des Transports) standard, ensuring that data exchanges meet established interoperability requirements.

=== Implementation ===
Many transport authorities use SIRI for their own purposes, although the exact extent of this usage is unclear. The multimodal information system in '''Nouvelle-Aquitaine''' (Modalis) utilizes NeTEx, or there are plans to implement it. Similarly, '''Île-de-France''' (IDFM) is also expected to adopt NeTEx for its multimodal information system.

=== Outcome ===
Currently, it is too early to observe the benefits of the NeTEx implementation, as the process is still ongoing. 

In the future, there are expectations for two key improvements: 

# The availability of more detailed information, including tariffs and accessibility of locations;
# Datasets with a higher level of quality. 

However, it is likely that in the coming years, a gap will emerge between the most advanced transport authorities and operators and those that are less advanced in their implementation of the NeTEx standard and multimodal information systems.</text>
      <sha1>nvqj1ralwdrovn74d3wn6ltjc33pgls</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Italy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>66</id>
    <revision>
      <id>599</id>
      <parentid>598</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-09-25T12:39:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Admin moved page [[Draft:Italy]] to [[Italy]]</comment>
      <origin>598</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8120" sha1="5ebef2uvrerw64hzi2y7iou5phmtrn9" xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:Country:Italy}}

= Overview in the National Level =

=== Italian NeTEx Profile ===
For the exchange of Public Transport (PT) data with Italian National Access Point (NAP), a NeTEx Profile has been defined among the affected stakeholders.

The profile is a subset of the standard; it has been defined selecting the needed concepts (entities and associated attributes) for specific use cases or set of use cases and complemented by rules defined to restrict possibilities of divergent interpretations of open parts of the standard.

The Italian NeTEx profile is structured in 5 levels, with the minimum objective of being able to have a protocol useful to transport of all the data categories required by the Del. Reg. 1926. It is currently used by stakeholders, few of them implemented the whole stack.
[[File:NeTEx Italian Profile.png|center|thumb|''Italian NeTEx Profile structure'']]

==== Passenger Information Profile (Level 1) ====

For the level 1 of the Italian NeTEx Profile, European Passenger Information Profile (EPIP) has been adopted as defined in the CEN Technical Specification CEN/TS 16614-4:2021.

Typical Passenger ''Information’s'' Use Cases are:

* provision of operativity calendars and timetables
* provision of network topology and routes
* provision of transport operators
* provision of access nodes to stop places

Main data categories exchanged are:

* Network topology:
** Stop
** Access nodes to the transport network
** Node geometry

* Timetables
* Validity calendars
* Lines
* Transport Operators

==== Contracts profile (Level 2) ====
For Contracts, Use Cases are:

* provision of Contract / Journey Accounting (with operator roles)
* provision of Stop Points Facilities (ticketing, accessibility, safety, etc.)
* provision of Vehicles Equipment (lift/ramps, wheelchair, etc.)


The level 2 of the Italian NeTEx Profile is defined upon the first level of European Passenger Information Profile (EPIP).

Main data categories exchanged are:

* Vehicle equipment (BUS, Trams, Trains):
** Characteristics (chassis, serial number, carriages, etc.)
** Capacity (no. of seats)
** Installed devices
** Services on board (WiFi, etc.)
* Parking:
** PK in structure
** Park&amp;Ride
* Service contracts

==== Fare (Level 3) ====
This level contains the structures to exchange data relevant tariffs and Fare products.

Main data categories exchanged are:

* Points of sale (TPL):
** Tickets for scheduled transport/on request
** Parking tickets
** Ticket offices
** Digital sales platforms
* Tariffs (TPL):
** Fare zones/bands/stops (O/D matrices, etc.)
** Standard fare structures (point-to-point, fixed, etc.)
* Classes of passengers (adults, children, students, elderly, disabled, etc.)
* Standard and special pricing products (offers, etc.)

==== Alternative Modes (Level 4) ====
This level deals with data relevant to sharing and micromobility.

Main data categories exchanged are:

* Network topology:
** Operational area of ​​the service
** Sharing stations
** TAXI stations
** Electric charging stations
* Parking: Secure parking spaces for bicycles
* Booking (sharing): Digital platforms
* Points of sale (sharing): Digital sales platforms
* Tariffs (sharing): Pricing structure

==== Accessibility (Level 5) ====
With this level of NeTEx profile is possible to exchange data relevant accessibility of PT Service. For the level 5 of the Italian NeTEx Profile, European Passenger Information Accessibility Profile (EPIAP) has been adopted as defined in the CEN Technical Specification CEN/TS 16614-6:2024.

Main data categories exchanged are:

* Accessibility of the transport network:
** Access nodes
** Internal routes in interchanges (e.g. elevators, escalators)
* Existence of user assistance services

=== Italian SIRI Profile ===
For the exchange of Public Transport (PT) dynamic data with Italian National Access Point (NAP), a SIRI Profile has been defined among the affected stakeholders.
[[File:SIRI Italian Profile.png|center|thumb|Italian SIRI Profile structure]]


The Italian SIRI Profile has been defined, basically EPIP-RT has been adopted. It includes following have been selected:

* '''SIRI-ET''': Estimated Timetable service: this function is defined by siri_estimatedTimetable_service.xsd and transfers vehicle passing times at stops already reached. In SIRI “2.1” for each stopping points, boarding and alighting passengers number are recorded.
* '''SIRI-VM''': Vehicle Monitoring service: this function is defined by siri_vehicleMonitoring_service.xsd and transfers real-time vehicle positions and/or stop point arrival/passing times with forecasts on next stopping points.
* '''SIRI-SX''': Situation Exchange service: this function is defined by siri_situationExchange_service.xsd and transfers events affecting regular PT service.
* '''SIRI-FM''': Facility Monitoring service: exchange real-time status of facilities at a stop (lifts, escalators, etc.)

=== NAP MMTIS ===
The Italian NeTEx profile is used to exchange with the NAP MMTIS (National Access Point Multi-Modal Travel Information Services) the transport information collected at regional level through collectors named RAP (Regional Access Points) and National Transport Operators. The following figure shows the architecture of this implementation:
[[File:Italian NAP MMTIS.png|center|thumb|600x600px|Italian NAP MMTIS architecture]]
National architecture design and implementation has been completed, it foresees the creation of an intermediate level between PTOs and NAP, called Regional Access Point (RAP), that will be one for each Italian region and will be managed by local PTAs or mobility agencies.

Implementation of this technical architecture implies also formalization through the signature of specific MOU, of relationships and responsibilities concerning data gathering and exchange of all stakeholders: PTOs, PTAs, Agencies and System Integrators

= Use cases = 

== Bolzano, STA (Südtiroler Transportstrukturen)==

STA (Südtiroler Transportstrukturen), is the in-house company working on behalf of the Public Transport Authority in Bolzano. 

STA is positioned in a unique location, is part of Italy but very close to Austria and the majority of the people speaks German. This means that the travel information STA offers (such as bus stop names) has to be multilingual. Therefore, there were needing a standard which allows them to exchange this kind of information considering the multilingual data. NeTEx provided this opportunity.   

[[File:STA 1.jpg|center|thumb|500x500px]]
[[File:STA 2.png|center|thumb|500x500px]]
=== System Architecture === 

STA opted to implement NeTEx and SIRI ‘natively’, meaning there is no conversion between the production of the data and NeTEx data files from another exchange data format. Considering the complex modelling that is needed to represent the physical environment of public transport, the complete standards NeTEx and SIRI were decided as more suitable.   
[[File:STA 3.png|center|thumb|500x500px|Challenges]]Based on the new architecture, NeTEx - SIRI, and other relevant standards, are implemented for the exchange of planned and real time data between back end systems (like operational planning tool ticketing system, travel planner and others. This architecture and the introduction of those standards is seen as the sustainable solution that can accommodate future developments on for example MaaS and integrated ticketing systems.   
[[File:SA 1.png|center|thumb|731x731px]]
[[File:SA 2.png|center|thumb|500x500px]]

=== Implementation ===
In particular this architecture was chosen to support also "LinkingAlps", one of the EU projects in which it is developed a decentralised network of travel information services. This network will be created by interlinking existing regional or national journey planner services from all neighbour countries, with focus on multimodal transport (public transport, railways, new modes) through a standardised exchange service. In this context, the exchange of complete and interoperable datasets is key.

=== Outcome ===
To be completed.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Country:Italy}}</text>
      <sha1>5ebef2uvrerw64hzi2y7iou5phmtrn9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Main Page</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1</id>
    <revision>
      <id>725</id>
      <parentid>724</parentid>
      <timestamp>2025-08-05T14:23:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Discover, Verify, Connect */</comment>
      <origin>725</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1548" sha1="74k9jeefgz22d6ye9uesdbhhr8l1bpo" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Data4PT logo flat.jpg|center|600px]]
&lt;big&gt;
= '''Welcome to the DATA4PT Wiki''' =
[[File:People Collaborating.png|right|400px]]

==Discover, Verify, Connect==
&lt;br&gt;
*'''Want to become aware of NAP and related standards?'''
[https://data4pt-project.eu/ Explore the DATA4PT project pages] and enjoy a wealth of knowledge!

*'''Need to verify your NeTEx data?'''
A NeTEx validation tool is planned to be delivered in the frame of the NAPCORE project. Meanwhile, [mailto:technical.support@itxpt.org?subject=NeTEx%20validation%20tool%20(from%20DATA4PT%20wiki) contact us here] for any questions or requests about this topic.

*'''Require support?'''
Don't hesitate! [https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1xQD5pPrxOFvoQrheQ0jpnFtWR3oWdCy5DyUZBRvWr0c/viewform?edit_requested=true Fill in a support request], and we're here to help.

*'''Like to comment on the available pages in the "Discussion" tab?'''
We value your input! [https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1xQD5pPrxOFvoQrheQ0jpnFtWR3oWdCy5DyUZBRvWr0c/viewform?edit_requested=true Contact us] and share your thoughts.

*'''Wish to contribute and create new pages?'''
[https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1xQD5pPrxOFvoQrheQ0jpnFtWR3oWdCy5DyUZBRvWr0c/viewform?edit_requested=true Join our expert community] and be part of something great!

==Why DATA4PT?==

DATA4PT is your one-stop destination for public transportation data, standards, and collaboration. Whether you're a newcomer or an expert, we're here to support your journey.

Join us in shaping the future of public transportation data together!
&lt;/big&gt;</text>
      <sha1>74k9jeefgz22d6ye9uesdbhhr8l1bpo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>National Access Points</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3</id>
    <revision>
      <id>9</id>
      <timestamp>2020-10-01T11:20:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Created blank page</comment>
      <origin>9</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="0" sha1="phoiac9h4m842xq45sp7s6u21eteeq1" xml:space="preserve" />
      <sha1>phoiac9h4m842xq45sp7s6u21eteeq1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>National Implementations</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>65</id>
    <revision>
      <id>642</id>
      <parentid>634</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-12-11T13:37:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anonymous</username>
        <id>13</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added austria link</comment>
      <origin>642</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="34911" sha1="h955ihn9vdjnoyjndolnyojww7crzz6" xml:space="preserve">= NeTEx national profiles inventory 🌐 =

A number of national and transnational profiles have already been defined for different European countries, while there are new profiles under development. In the following tables, DATA4PT provides an overview of the '''key characteristics of the national profiles per country''', including the data categories that are currently covered. The tables will be continuously updated following new implementations.    

== Published profiles ==

{| class="wikitable" style="width : 60%"
|-
! width="150px"| Profile Name 
!Status/
Availability
! width="100px" | NeTEx EPIP Based* !! width="100px" | NeTEx EPIP Compatible** 
! width="300px" | Documentation
|-
| Australia - Victoria (AU) 
|Specified but not yet in operation
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
|
|-
|Austria (AT)
|Specified but not yet in operation|| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| ||[https://mobilitaetsverbuende.atlassian.net/wiki/spaces/NET/overview Austrian profile]
|-
|Belgium (BE)
|Specified but not yet in operation|| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| ||[https://github.com/Informatievlaanderen/OSLOthema-mobiliteitDienstregelingEnPlanning GitHUb]
[https://purl.eu/doc/applicationprofile/netex-belgium/timetables-ap/ AP-Timetables]

[https://purl.eu/doc/applicationprofile/netex-belgium/stopplaces-ap/ AP-Stops]

[https://purl.eu/doc/applicationprofile/netex-belgium/vehiclescheduling-ap/ AP-Vehicle Scheduling]

[https://purl.eu/ns/mobility/timetables-and-planning/ AP-TimetablesAndPlanning]

[https://github.com/Informatievlaanderen/OSLOthema-mobiliteitDienstregelingEnPlanning/tree/master/resources/DataExamples Data examples]
|-
|Croatia (HR)
|Specified and in use
| style="text-align:center;" | ✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
|[https://www.promet-info.hr/en NPT - Croatian NAP]
|-
|Denmark (DK)
|Specified but not yet in operation|| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| ||[https://www.trafikstyrelsen.dk/Media/638013312835439194/Vejledning%20om%20brug%20af%20NeTEx.pdf Denmark profile] - [https://www.trafikstyrelsen.dk/arbejdsomraader/kollektiv-trafik/statistik-og-data/krav-til-udstilling-af-data-til-rejseplanlaegning NAP in Denmark]
|-
|France (FR)
|Specified and in use|| || style="text-align:center;" |✅||[https://normes.transport.data.gouv.fr/normes/netex/ French profile] - [https://normes.transport.data.gouv.fr/normes/netex/elements_communs/ Common profile] - [https://normes.transport.data.gouv.fr/normes/netex/arrets/ Stop profile] - [https://normes.transport.data.gouv.fr/normes/netex/reseaux/ Network profile] - [https://normes.transport.data.gouv.fr/normes/netex/horaires/ Timetable profile] - [https://normes.transport.data.gouv.fr/normes/netex/tarifs/ Fare profile] - [https://normes.transport.data.gouv.fr/normes/netex/parkings/ Parking profile] - [https://normes.transport.data.gouv.fr/normes/netex/accessibilite/ Accessibility profile]
|-
|Italy (IT)
|Specified and in use|| style="text-align:center;" |✅||
|[https://github.com/5Tsrl/netex-italian-profile/tree/main/Linee%20guida Italian profile]
|-
|Netherlands (NL) 
|Specified but not yet in operation|| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| ||[https://bison.dova.nu/standaarden/nederlands-netex-profiel Netherlands profile] - [https://bison.dova.nu/sites/default/files/bison_prijzen_producten_en_tarieven_v8.1.3.0_release.pdf Bison Fares]
|-
| Nordic (Norway, Sweden, Finland, Denmark)
|Specified and in use|| || style="text-align:center;" |✅||[https://enturas.atlassian.net/wiki/spaces/PUBLIC/pages/728891481/Nordic+NeTEx+Profile Nordic profile]
|-
|Portugal (PT)
|Specified and in use|| || ||[https://ptprofiles.azurewebsites.net/netex-profile Portuguese profile]
|-
| Slovenia (SI)
|Specified but not yet in operation|| || style="text-align:center  " |✅||[https://www.nap.si/_resources/profiles/NeTEx_SI_Profile_v2.pdf Slovenian profile]
|-
|Switzerland (CH)
|Specified and in use
|
|
|[https://www.oev-info.ch/sites/default/files/2024-05/NeTEx_Core-Realisation_Guide_TP_Suisse-v1.00.pdf Swiss profile]
|-
|UK (GB)
|Specified and in use|| || style="text-align:center  " |✅||[http://netex.uk/farexchange/ UK profile] - [http://netex.uk/farexchange/doc/uk_profile/DfT-NeTEx-1-Fares-Intro-2019.06.17-v0.09.pdf Introduction] - [http://netex.uk/farexchange/doc/uk_profile/DfT-NeTEx-2-Base_Spec-2019.06.30-v0.14.pdf Stop and Timetables] - [http://netex.uk/farexchange/doc/uk_profile/DfT-NeTEx-3-Fares_Spec-2019.06.17-v0.17.pdf Fares]
|-
|Ireland (IE)
|Specified and in use|| || ||[https://netex.ie/ Irish profile] - [http://netex.uk/netexie/doc/EIRE_NP/NTA-NeTEx-1-Spec-2020.08.12-v0.22.pdf Profile Elements] - [http://netex.uk/netexie/doc/EIRE_NP/NTA-NeTEx-2-Mappings-2020.08.06-v0.22.pdf Profile Data Mappings]
|-
|Czech Republic (CZ)
|Specified but not yet in operation
| style="text-align:center  " |✅
|
|
|}
&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt;Profiles of this category have been specified based on EU Minimum profile and are based on XML technology as EU profiles.  

&lt;nowiki&gt;**&lt;/nowiki&gt; Profiles of this category have been specified either before the definition of EU Minimum profile, but they have been used to define the EU one, and/or after EU profiles and need conversion or adaptation to be interoperable.
==Data categories==

''Data categories are identified based on [https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=celex%3A32024R0490 MMTIS EU Regulation 490/2024]''
{| class="mw-collapsible mw-collapsed wikitable" style="width:70%"
|+ style="white-space:nowrap; border:1px solid; padding:3px;" | Data categories table.
|-
!Level of service (LOS)!!Static data
|-
| colspan="2" style="text-align:center " bgcolor="#A6C9EC" |'''Static data - Level of service 1 (LOS 1 )'''
|-
| colspan="2" |'''a. Location search (origin/destination)'''
|-
|LOS 1-1||Address identifiers (building number, street name, postcode)
|-
| LOS 1-2||Topographic places (city, town, village, suburb, administrative unit)
|-
|LOS 1-3||Points of interest (related to transport information) to which people may wish to travel
|-
|LOS 1-4||'''b. Trip plans: operational calendar, mapping day types to calendar dates'''
|-
| colspan="2" |'''c. Location search (access nodes) – for scheduled transport and transport on demand where relevant'''
|-
|LOS 1-5
| Identified access nodes
|-
|LOS 1-6 ||Geometry/map layout structure of access nodes

|-
| colspan="2" |'''d. Trip plan computation – for scheduled transport and transport on demand where relevant'''
|-
|LOS 1-7||Connection where interchanges may be made
|-
|LOS 1-8
|Default transfer times at interchanges
|-
|LOS 1-9||Network topology and routes/lines (topology)
|-
| LOS 1-10|| Transport operators
|-
|LOS 1-11|| Timetables
|-
|LOS 1-12||Planned interchanges between guaranteed scheduled services
|-
|LOS 1-13||Hours of operation
|-
| LOS 1-14
|Facilities of access nodes (including platform information, help desk/information points, ticket booths, lifts/stairs, entrances and exit locations)
|-
|LOS 1-15||Vehicles, including their accessibility (such as low floor, wheelchair accessible, pram accessible) and accessibility of on-board services (such as toilets)
|-
|LOS 1-16||Accessibility of access nodes, and paths within an interchange (such as existence of lifts, escalators)
|-
|LOS 1-17||Existence of assistance services (such as existence of on-site assistance)
|-
| colspan="2" |'''e. Trip plan computation'''
|-
|LOS 1-18||Road network (including segregated lanes for bus/taxi)
|-
|LOS 1-19||Cycle network (cycle tracks, cycle lanes, bus-and-cycle lanes, on-road shared with vehicles, on-path shared with pedestrians)
|-
|LOS 1-20||Pedestrian network and accessibility facilities
|-
| ||Framework data
|-
|
|
|-
| colspan="2" style="text-align:center " bgcolor="#A6C9EC" |'''Static data - Level of service 2 (LOS 2)'''
|-
| colspan="2" |'''a. Location search – for transport on demand and personal transport'''
|-
|LOS 2-1
|Location of parking places (on and off-street), including accessible parking places for persons with disabilities and persons with reduced mobility
|-
|LOS 2-2||Park &amp; Ride stops
|-
|LOS 2-3
| Park &amp; Drive stops
|-
|LOS 2-4||Bike sharing stations
|-
|LOS 2-5||Car-sharing stations
|-
| LOS 2-6
|Secure bike parking (such as locked bike garages)
|-
|LOS 2-7
|Scooter parking zones
|-
| colspan="2" |'''b. Information service'''
|-
|LOS 2-8||Where and how to buy tickets for scheduled transport, including retail channels, fulfilment methods, payment methods
|-
|LOS 2-9||Where and how to pay for parking, including retail channels, fulfilment methods, payment methods
|-
| colspan="2" |'''c. Auxiliary information – for scheduled transport and transport on demand where relevant'''
|-
|LOS 2-10 ||Basic common standard fares
- fare network data (fare zones/stops and fare stages)

- standard fare structures (point to point including daily and weekly fares, zonal fares, flat fares)
|-
|LOS 2-11||Vehicle facilities such as classes of carriage, on-board Wi-Fi.
|-
| ||
|-
| colspan="2" style="text-align:center " bgcolor="#A6C9EC" |'''Static data - Level of service 3 (LOS 3''') 
|-
| colspan="2" |'''a. Detailed common standard and special fare query – for scheduled transport and transport on demand where relevant'''
|-
|LOS 3-1||Passenger classes (classes of passenger such as adult, child, senior, student, military/veteran, passenger with disability and passenger with reduced mobility, and qualifying conditions, and classes of travel)
|-
|LOS 3-2|| Common fare products (access rights such as zone/point-to-point including daily and weekly tickets/single/return, eligibility of access, basic usage conditions such as validity period/operator/time of travel/interchanging, standard point-to-point fares prices for different point-to-point pairs including daily and weekly fares/zonal fare prices/flat fare prices)
|-
|LOS 3-3||Special fare products (offers with additional special conditions such as promotional fares, group fares, season passes, aggregated products combining different products, and add-on products such as parking and travel, minimum stay) 
|-
|LOS 3-4|| Basic commercial conditions such as refunding, replacing, exchanging or transferring
|-
|LOS 3-5||Basic booking conditions such as purchase windows, validity periods, routing restrictions zonal sequence fares, minimum stay
|-
|LOS 3-6||'''b. Information service – for transport on demand: how to book demand-responsive transport services, including retail channels, fulfilment methods, payment methods'''
|-
| colspan="2" |'''c. Trip plans'''
|-
|LOS 3-7||Detailed cycle network attributes (surface quality, side-by-side cycling, shared surface, on/off road, scenic route, “walk only”, turn or access restrictions, e.g. against flow of traffic)
|-
|LOS 3-8 ||Parameters needed to calculate an environmental factor such as greenhouse gas emissions per vehicle type or passenger mile or per distance walked
|-
|LOS 3-9||Parameters needed to calculate fuel consumption of conventional and alternative fuels
|-
|LOS 3-10
|'''d. Trip plan computation: estimated travel times by day type and time-band by transport mode/combination of transport mode'''
|-
| colspan="2" |
|-
| colspan="2" style="text-align:center " bgcolor="#A6C9EC" |'''Static data - Level of service 4 (LOS 4 )'''
|-
| LOS 4-1
|'''a. Historic travel and traffic data on delays – for scheduled transport and transport on demand where relevant'''
|-
| colspan="2" |'''b. Observed data on delays and passing time – for scheduled transport'''
|-
|LOS 4-2
|Length of, and when possible the reason for, delays of at least 60 minutes for rail passenger services (in accordance with Article 19 of Regulation (EU) 2021/782)
|-
|LOS 4-3
|Length of, and when possible the reason for, delays in departure of more than 90 minutes for sea and inland waterways passenger services (in accordance with Article 18 of Regulation (EU) No 1177/2010) 
|-
|LOS 4-4
| Length of, and when possible the reason for, delays in departure from a terminal of more than 120 minutes for regular bus and coach passenger services with a scheduled distance of 250 km or more (in accordance with Article 19 of Regulation (EU) No 181/2011)
|-
|LOS 4-5
|Length of, and when possible the reason for, flight delays at departure of at least 120 minutes; and flight delays at arrival of at least 180 minutes (in accordance with Articles 5 and 6 of Regulation (EC) No 261/2004)
|-
| colspan="2" |'''c. Observed data on cancellations – for scheduled transport'''
|-
|LOS 4-6
|Cancellations, and when possible the reason, of rail passenger services
|-
|LOS 4-7 
|Cancellations, and when possible the reason, of sea and inland waterways passenger services
|-
|LOS 4-8
|Cancellations, and when possible the reason, of regular bus and coach services with a scheduled distance of 250 km or more
|-
|LOS 4-9
|Cancellations, and when possible the reason, of flights
|-
|LOS 4-10
|'''d. Information on parking tariffs'''
|}

==Static data - Level of service 1 (LOS 1)==

{| class="wikitable" style="width:70%"
|-
! width="80px" |Data Categories

! width="80px" style="text-align:center " |EPIP
! width="80px" |AU
! width="80px" |AT
! width="80px" |BE
! width="80px" |HR 
! width="80px" |DK 
! width="80px" |FR
! width="80px" |IT
! width="80px" |NL
! width="150px" |Nordic (SE, NOR, DK, FIN)
! width="80px" |PT
! width="80px" |SI
! width="80px" |CH
! width="80px" |GB
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-1]]||
| ||
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅ || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " | ✅
| ||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-2]]||
| style="text-align:center;" |✅||
| style="text-align:center " | ✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| || style="text-align:center " |✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-3]]||
| ||
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| ||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-4]]||
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅ || style="text-align:center " | ✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " | ✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " | ✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-5]]||
| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " | ✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |defined in profile||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-6]]||
| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| ||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-7]]||
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
| || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-8]]
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-9]]|| style="text-align:center " | ✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅ 
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅
| || style="text-align:center " |✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-10]]|| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅ 
| style="text-align:center;" |✅ || style="text-align:center " |✅ || style="text-align:center " |✅ || style="text-align:center " |✅ || style="text-align:center " |✅ || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-11]]|| style="text-align:center " |✅ 
| style="text-align:center;" | ✅ || style="text-align:center " | ✅ 
| style="text-align:center " | ✅ 
| style="text-align:center;" | ✅ || style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅ 
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-12]]||
| style="text-align:center;" | ✅ || style="text-align:center " | ✅ 
|
| || style="text-align:center " |not existent|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |For connection links we use journey planner based on OSM map data, road, cycle, and pedestrian network is based on OpenStreetMap || || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-13]]||
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" | ✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " | ✅ || || style="text-align:center " | ✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |partially covered||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-14]]
|
|
|
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|
|
|
| style="text-align:center;" |partially covered
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-15]]||
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" | ✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅ || style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅ 
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |partially covered||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-16]]||
| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅ 
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| ||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-17]]||
| ||
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅ || || style="text-align:center " |✅ || || style="text-align:center " |✅
| ||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-18]]||
| ||
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| || style="text-align:center " | || || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| ||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-19]]||
| ||
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| || style="text-align:center " | || || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| ||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-20]]||
| ||
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| ||
|-
| Framework data||
| ||
|
| || || || || || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| 
| ||
|-
|}

==Static data - Level of service 2 (LOS 2)==

{| class="wikitable" style="width:70%"
|-
! width="80px" |Data Categories 
! width="80px" style="text-align:center " |EPIP
! width="80px" | AU
! width="80px" |AT 
! width="80px" |ΒΕ
! width="80px" |HR
! width="80px" |DK 
! width="80px" |FR
! width="80px" |IT
! width="80px" |NL
! width="150px" |Nordic (SE, NOR, DK, FIN)
! width="80px" |PT
! width="80px" |SI
! width="80px" |CH
! width="80px" |GB
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-1]]
|
|
|
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
|
| style="text-align:center;" |for off-street only
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|
|
| |
| style="text-align:center;" |partially covered
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-2]]||
| ||
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |partially covered||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-3]]
|
|
|
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|
|
|
| style="text-align:center;" |partially covered
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-4]]||
| ||
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " | ✅
| style="text-align:center;" |partially covered||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-5]]||
| ||
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |partially covered||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-6]]||
| ||
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |in off-street car parks only|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-7]]
|
|
|
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|
|
|
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-8]]||
| ||
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| ||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-9]]
|
|
|
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
| style="text-align:center " | ✅
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-10]]||
| style="text-align:center;" |✅||
|
| || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " | ✅
| || style="text-align:center " |✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-11]]||
| style="text-align:center;" |✅||
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| || || style="text-align:center " | ✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| || style="text-align:center " |✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-12]]||
| ||
|
| || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| || style="text-align:center " | ✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-13]]||
| ||
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " | ✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| || style="text-align:center " |✅
|-
|}

==Static data - Level of service 3 (LOS 3)==

{| class="wikitable" style="width:70%"
|-
! width="80px" |Data Categories
! width="80px" style="text-align:center " |EPIP
! width="80px" |AU
! width="80px" |AT
! width="80px" |BE
! width="80px" |HR
! width="80px" |DK
! width="80px" |FR
! width="80px" |IT
! width="80px" |NL
! width="150px" |Nordic (SE, NOR, DK, FIN)
! width="80px" |PT 
! width="80px" |SI 
! width="80px" |CH
! width="80px" |GB
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 3-1]]||
| ||
| style="text-align:center " |✅

| style="text-align:center " | ✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅ || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || 
| || style="text-align:center " | ✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 3-2]]||
| ||
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || 
| || style="text-align:center " |✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 3-3]]||
| ||
|
| || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || 
| || style="text-align:center " |✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 3-4]]
|
|
|
|
|
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|
|
|
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 3-5]]
|
|
|
|
|
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 3-6]]
|
|
|
|
|
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
|
|
|
|
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 3-7]]||
| ||
|
| || || || || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || 
| ||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 3-8]]||
| ||
|
| || || style="text-align:center;" |✅|| || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || 
| ||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 3-9]]||
| ||
|
| || || style="text-align:center;" |✅|| || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || 
| ||
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 3-10]]||
| ||
|
| || || || || || style="text-align:center " |✅|| || 
| style="text-align:center;" |N/A||
|-
|}

==Static data - Level of service 4 (LOS 4) ==
{| class="wikitable" style="width:70%"
|-
! width="80px" |Data Categories 
! width="80px" style="text-align:center " |EPIP
! width="80px" |AU
! width="80px" |AT
! width="80px" |BE
! width="80px" |HR
! width="80px" |DK
! width="80px" |FR
! width="80px" |IT
! width="80px" |NL
! width="150px" |Nordic (SE, NOR, DK, FIN)
! width="80px" |PT
! width="80px" |SI 
! width="80px" |CH
! width="80px" |GB
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 4-1]]||
| ||
|
| || || style="text-align:center " | || || || style="text-align:center " | || || 
| || style="text-align:center " |
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 4-2]]
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 4-3]]
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 4-4]]
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 4-5]]
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 4-6]]
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 4-7]]
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 4-8]]
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 4-9]]
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 4-10]]
|
|
|
|
|
|
| style="text-align:center;" |✅ 
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|
|
|
|
|
|}

⚠️ If you believe that your use cases are resolved in an existing profile, it is highly recommended to '''adopt an existing solution''' and cooperate with the corresponding entity. You will save resources while you will ensure that your profile is interoperable.

📄 You can also find contact details for some of the entities responsible for the profiles in the documentation list. Otherwise you can contact us in [https://data4pt-project.eu/requests-requirements/ DATA4PT].

=SIRI National profiles inventory 🌐=

National profiles are specified to cover the national needs. To help implementation, DATA4PT is also in process of delivering SIRI EU minimum profile, in collaboration with relevant CEN group. DATA4PT has prepared a table with the currently available SIRI national profiles, including an overview of data categories that are currently covered. For data categories relevant to static data check the [NeTEx Profiles Inventory https://data4pt.org/w/index.php?title=NeTEX#NeTEx_national_and_EU_minimum_profiles_inventory].

==Published profiles==

{| class="wikitable" style="width : 50%"
|-
!Profile Name!!Status/
Availability 
!EU Minimum profile based*!!EU Minimum SIRI profile compatible** !!Documentation
|-
|Australia - Victoria (AU)
|Specified but not yet in operation 
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|-
|Croatia (HR)
|Using an existing profile
|
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|-
|France (FR)||Specified and in use
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center;" | ||[https://normes.transport.data.gouv.fr/normes/siri/profil-france/ French SIRI profile]
|-
|Italy (IT)
| Specified and in use
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|[https://github.com/5Tsrl/siri-italian-profile/tree/main/Linee%20guida Italian SIRI profile]
|-
|Netherlands (NL)||Specified but not yet in operation 
| || style="text-align:center;" |✅||
|-
|Nordic (Norway, Sweden, Finland, Denmark)|| Specified and in use
| || style="text-align:center;" |✅||[https://enturas.atlassian.net/wiki/spaces/PUBLIC/pages/637370420/Nordic+SIRI+Profile Nordic SIRI profile]
|-
|UK (GB) ||Specified and in use
| || style="text-align:center;" |✅||
|-
|Switzerland (CH)
|Specified and in use
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
|[https://www.oev-info.ch/sites/default/files/2023-04/siri_realisation-guide_pt_ch_v0.9.0.pdf SIRI-ET/PT][https://www.oev-info.ch/sites/default/files/2024-07/realization_guide_siri-sx_oev_schweiz_v1.0.pdf SIRI-SX]
|}
&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt;Profiles of this category have been specified based on EU Minimum profile and are based on XML technology as EU profiles. 

&lt;nowiki&gt;**&lt;/nowiki&gt; Profiles of this category have been specified either before the definition of EU Minimum profile, but they have been used to define the EU one, and/or after EU profiles and need conversion or adaptation to be interoperable.
==Data categories==

''Data categories are identified based on [https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=celex%3A32024R0490 MMTIS EU Regulation 490/2024]''
{| class="mw-collapsible mw-collapsed wikitable" style="width : 60%"
|+ style="white-space:nowrap; border:1px solid; padding:3px;" |Data categories table.
|-
!Level of service (LOS)!!Types of the dynamic travel and traffic data
|-
| colspan="2" style="text-align:center " bgcolor="#A6C9EC" |'''Dynamic data - Level of service 1 (LOS 1 )'''
|-
| colspan="2" |'''a. Passing times, trip plans and auxiliary information'''
|-
| LOS 1-1||Disruptions, such as network closures and/or diversions, and when possible, the reason 
|-
|LOS 1-2||Real-time status information, such as estimated departure and arrival times of services, delays, cancellations, guaranteed connections monitoring
|-
|LOS 1-3||Status of access node features (including dynamic platform information, operational lifts/escalators, closed entrances and exit locations) – for scheduled transport
|-
| colspan="2" style="text-align:center " bgcolor="#A6C9EC" |'''Dynamic data - Level of service 2 (LOS 2)'''
|-
|LOS 2-1||'''a. Information service on parking tariffs – for transport on demand and personal transport'''
|-
| colspan="2" |'''b. Availability check and location – for transport on demand and personal transport where relevant'''
|-
|LOS 2-2||Car-sharing availability and location, bike-sharing availability and location, scooter-sharing availability and location, and other vehicle-sharing availability and location
|-
|LOS 2-3||Car parking spaces available (on and off-street)
|-
| colspan="2" style="text-align:center " bgcolor="#A6C9EC" |'''Dynamic data - Level of service 3 (LOS 3''') 
|-
|LOS 3-1|| Occupancy information of the vehicle – for scheduled transport and transport on demand where relevant
|}

==Dynamic data - Level of service 1 (LOS 1) ==

{| class="wikitable" style="width : 30%"
|-
!Data Categories
! width="80px" |AU
! width="80px" |HR
! width="80px" |FR
! width="80px" |IT
! width="80px" |NL
! width="300px" |Nordic (SE, NOR, DK, FIN)
! width="80px" |GB
! width="80px" |CH
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-1]]
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅ &lt;br&gt;dynamic platform is included || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-2]]
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅ &lt;br&gt;dynamic platform is included || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 1-3]]
| || || style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅|| style="text-align:center " |✅ &lt;br&gt;dynamic platform is included || style="text-align:center " |
| style="text-align:center;" |✅
via SX
|-
|}

==Dynamic data - Level of service 2 (LOS 2) ==

{| class="wikitable" style="width : 30%"
|-
!Data Categories
! width="80px" |AU
! width="80px" |HR
! width="80px" | FR
! width="80px" |IT
! width="80px" |NL
! width="300px" |Nordic (SE, NOR, DK, FIN)
! width="80px" |GB
! width="80px" |CH
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-1]]
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-2]]
| || || style="text-align:center " |only for car sharing and bike sharing
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅||
|
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 2-3]]
| || || style="text-align:center " |off-street only
| style="text-align:center " |✅|| || style="text-align:center " |✅||
|
|-
|}

==Dynamic data - Level of service 3 (LOS 3) ==

{| class="wikitable" style="width : 30%"
|-
!Data Categories
! width="80px" |AU
! width="80px" |FR
! width="80px" |IT
! width="80px" |NL
! width="300px" |Nordic (SE, NOR, DK, FIN)
! width="80px" |GB
! width="80px" |CH
|-
|[[#Data categories|LOS 3-1]]
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅
| style="text-align:center " |✅
|
|
|
|
|}

⚠️ If you believe that your use cases are resolved in an existing profile, it is highly recommended to '''adopt an existing solution''' and cooperate with the corresponding entity. You will save resources while you will ensure that your profile is interoperable.

📄 You can also find contact details for some of the entities responsible for the profiles in the documentation list. Otherwise you can contact us in [https://data4pt-project.eu/requests-requirements/ DATA4PT].

=Implementations per Country=
Currently, the implementations of NeTEx and SIRI are documented for the following countries:

====== [[Australia]] ======

====== [[Austria]] ======

====== [[Belgium]] ======

====== [[Croatia]] ======

====== [[Denmark]] ======

====== [[France]] ======

====== [[Italy]] ======

====== [[Portugal]] ======

====== [[Slovenia]] ======

====== [[Sweden]] ======

====== [[Switzerland]] ======</text>
      <sha1>h955ihn9vdjnoyjndolnyojww7crzz6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>NeTEX</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10</id>
    <revision>
      <id>728</id>
      <parentid>727</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-23T13:19:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anasfou</username>
        <id>5</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* NeTEx European Passenger Information Profile 🇪🇺 */</comment>
      <origin>728</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="15217" sha1="kk2ojul1ytyi5lmhi5ici18rc68rhns" xml:space="preserve">
= NeTEx overview 🔍 =
== What is NeTEx? ==

[[File:NeTEx.png|250px|right|]]

NeTEx (Network Exchange format) is a standard for exchanging public transport network, schedules, and related data. It is a general-purpose XML format designed for the efficient exchange of complex transport data among distributed systems.

It has been developed under the aegis of CEN (Comité Européen de Normalisation) and is the most recent development stage in over fifteen years work to systemise and harmonize European passenger information data.

NeTEx can be used to collect and integrate data from many different stakeholders, and to reintegrate it as it evolves through successive versions. It is used by public transport operators and IT providers across Europe to support a wide range of passenger information and operational applications.

== Benefits of using NeTEx ==

NeTEx offers a number of benefits, including:

* '''Flexibility''': NeTEx can be used to represent a wide range of public transport data, including networks, schedules, fares, and real-time information.
* '''Extensibility''': NeTEx can be extended to support new types of data and functionality.
* '''Interoperability''': NeTEx is a standard format, which means that data can be exchanged between different systems without the need for custom development.
* '''Support for modern web services architectures''' : NeTEx can be used to develop modern, web-based passenger information and operational applications.

== Examples of NeTEx in use ==

NeTEx is used in a variety of ways across the public transport industry. For example:

*'''Passenger information''': NeTEx can be used to provide real-time arrival and departure information to passengers, generate timetables and journey planners, and develop mobile apps for passengers.
*'''Operational applications''': NeTEx can be used to manage fleet operations, integrate public transport data with other systems, such as traffic management systems and navigation apps, and support planning and analysis.


ℹ️ To find out more about the NeTEX data model, visit the [https://transmodel-cen.eu/ Transmodel website].

= NeTEx European Passenger Information Profile 🇪🇺 =

{| class="wikitable"
!
! Description
! Documentation
|-
|width="150px" style="text-align:center |'''NeTEx EPIP'''|| Ideally, all member states will provide NeTEx files according to the European Passenger Information Profile (EPIP) on their respective National Access Point. Data4PT provides some artefacts to simplify producing and quality assure such information. EPIP-adapted version of the full NeTEx XML schema has been produced.
Moreover, since the official NeTEx schema is too large and complex for C# code generation tools to handle, a simplified version was created for application development. This schema has been reduced to only match the scope of the EPIP Profile (European Passenger Information Profile). It is compliant with the main NeTEx schema, but does not contain constraint checks and should not be used for validation.
| The documentation is available at the NeTEx GitHub repository [https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx-Profile-EPIP here]
|}


= Software &amp; tools 🧰 =

An ecosystem of NeTEx XML tools is under development, including both open-source and commercial products.

The following list of software is known to support NeTEx. We distinguish between different categories that may later receive a list of key performance indicators.

== XML tools ==
General purpose XML tools can be used to work with the NeTEx XML schema and XML documents that conform to it.

{| class="wikitable" style="width : 10%"
|-
!  width="80px"|XML tools
!  width="80px"|Description
|-
|[http://www.altova.com/xmlspy.html XML SPY] || commercial
|-
|[http://www.oxygenxml.com/ Oxygen]|| commercial
|-
|[http://www.garshol.priv.no/download/xmltools/ List of tools] || open-source
|-
{| class="wikitable"

== Conversion tools ==

{| class="wikitable" style="width:80%"
! colspan="1" | Name
! Availability
! width="40%" | |Description
! colspan="1" |Profile
!width="20%"| License
|-
| style="text-align:center |'''[https://github.com/entur/netex-protobuf netex-protobuf]''' ||style="text-align:center |✅ || NeTEx to protobuf converter || All ||EUPL
|-
|style="text-align:center | '''[https://github.com/CanalTP/transit_model/tree/master/gtfs2netexfr gtfs2netexfr]''' || style="text-align:center |✅ ||Export GTFS data to NeTEx. ||French    ||    
|-
| style="text-align:center |'''[https://github.com/skinkie/hastus hastus]''' || style="text-align:center |✅ ||Giro Hastus OIG script to export NeTEx from a system, in addition can export crew operations. ||Dutch, Nordic(?) || AGPL-3.0
|-
| style="text-align:center |'''[https://gitlab.com/labiangashi/josm-plugin-netex-converter/ josm-plugin-netex-converter]''' ||style="text-align:center |✅ || Export OpenStreetMap pedestrian routing information into NeTEx.||    || GPL 2.0   
|-
| style="text-align:center |'''[https://github.com/entur/netex-gtfs-converter-java netex-gtfs-converter-java]''' ||style="text-align:center |✅ || Export NeTEx data to GTFS ||Nordic ||EUPL
|-
|style="text-align:center |'''[https://github.com/cefriel/chimera Chimera]''' ||style="text-align:center |✅ || Chimera is a framework for semantic data transformation pipelines. A converter between GTFS and NeTEx has been implemented adopting an intermediate Transmodel representation. ||Nordic (ready), EPIP/Italian (ongoing) || Framework – Apache License 2.0, Mapping GTFS-NeTEx – Proprietary license
|-
|style="text-align:center |'''[https://www.openmove.com/ OpenMove ATLAS]''' || style="text-align:center |✅ || The management platform OpenMove ATLAS allows import and editing of data in GTFS format and export also in GTFS or NeTEx format (currently the Italian Profile is supported, other profiles can be implemented on request). || EPIP Italian ||Proprietary license
|-
|style="text-align:center |'''[https://developers.italia.it/it/software/a4c48ddf-7156-4327-a62b-66fc15f1c6f3 GTFS2NeTEx-converter]''' ||style="text-align:center |✅ || Converts GTFS data in NeTEx Italian Profile. || EPIP Italian Profile  ||EUPL 1.2
|}

== Data validation tools ==

{| class="wikitable" style="width:40%;"
! width="25%" | Name
!width="10%" | Availability
! width="40%"|  Description
!width="10%" | Profile
!width="10%" | License
|-
| style="text-align:center |'''[http://www.xmlsoft.org/ XMLlint]''' || style="text-align:center |✅ ||XML syntax validation, XSD schema validation and constraint checking. ||All ||MIT  
|-
|style="text-align:center | ''' The Data4PT Validation tool''' ||style="text-align:center |✅||The tool is under maintenance in the framework of [https://napcore.eu/ NAPCORE]. ||All ||
|-
| style="text-align:center |'''[https://github.com/entur/netex-validator-java NeTEx validator java]''' ||style="text-align:center |✅|| Validation library for NeTEx data, analyzing and reporting schema compliance. ||Nordic ||
|-
| style="text-align:center |'''[https://github.com/entur/antu Antu]''' ||style="text-align:center |✅|| Validate NeTEx datasets against the Nordic NeTEx Profile. ||Nordic || 	
|}

== Language bindings ==
{| class="wikitable" style="width: 45%;"
! Name
! Availability
! Description
! Profile
! License
|-
| style="text-align:center |'''[https://github.com/entur/netex-java-model netex-java-model]''' || style="text-align:center |✅ ||NeTEx XML bindings for Java, with additions to map temporal types to native objects. ||All ||EUPL
|-
|style="text-align:center | '''netex-csharp-model''' ||style="text-align:center |❌ || NeTEx XML bindings for C#. Currently being researched with a variety of tools.&lt;br&gt;Contact DATA4PT if you have questions or have found the golden egg. ||All ||
|-
|style="text-align:center | '''[https://github.com/entur/netex-parser-java netex-parser-java]''' ||style="text-align:center |✅||Parse NeTEx files and lookup entities in an index ||Nordic ||EUPL
|-
|}

== Editing /Management &amp; visualisation tools ==

{| class="wikitable" style="width: 75%;"
! Name
! Availability
! Description
! Profile
! License
! URL
|-
| style="text-align:center | '''Nplan''' ||style="text-align:center | ✅|| Java backend / TypeScript frontend for create/edit/export of NeTEx data (Support both Timetable based and On-demand polygon based services) ||Nordic ||EUPL ||backend - https://github.com/entur/uttu &lt;br&gt; frontend - https://github.com/entur/enki
|-
|style="text-align:center |'''NSR''' ||style="text-align:center | ✅|| Java backend / JavaScript frontend for import/creation/edit/export for NeTEx stops data. (Act as a National Stops Register for the whole of Norway) || Nordic ||EUPL ||backend - https://github.com/entur/tiamat &lt;br&gt; frontend - https://github.com/entur/abzu
|-
| style="text-align:center |'''Chouette'''|| style="text-align:center |✅|| Java backend / Ruby frontend for import/validation/edit/export of NeTEx data. Highly modified version of the old AFIMB version of Chouette. NOTE: Legacy software not recommended for new implemetations ||Nordic ||CeCILL-B ||backend - https://github.com/entur/chouette &lt;br&gt; frontend -  https://github.com/entur/chouette2
|-
|style="text-align:center |'''[https://enroute.mobi/produits/chouette/ Chouette]''' ||style="text-align:center | ✅|| Java based NeTEx tools, transforms between profiles and standards (NeTEx, GTFS, Neptune). ||EPIP ||Apache 2.0 ||
|-
|style="text-align:center |'''[https://mobilitx.diginext.fr/ mobilitx]''' || style="text-align:center |✅|| || || ||
|-
|style="text-align:center |'''[https://www.lumiplan.com/produit/mobiref/ mobiref]''' ||style="text-align:center | ✅ || || || ||
|-
|style="text-align:center |'''NeTEx Reader''' ||style="text-align:center | ⏳ ||C# based XML tool based on Giro Hastus XSD || Dutch || ||https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mpb_1Y9uR5k
|-
|style="text-align:center |'''netexconv2''' || style="text-align:center |⏳ ||Java based NeTEx tools, transforms between profiles and standards (NeTEx, DINO, HAFAS, KV1, GTFS). || Dutch, EPIP, Nordic, VDV462 || ||
|-
|style="text-align:center | '''[https://www.ivu.com/news/news/article/delfi-successfully-migrates-to-ivucloud.html IVU.cloud]''' || style="text-align:center |✅|| ||EPIP || ||
|-
|style="text-align:center |'''[https://www.pluservice.net/it/soluzioni/gestione-rete-e-turni Motus]''' ||style="text-align:center | ✅|| 4Motus is the Fleet Scheduling Management System provided by Pluservice. The application is designed by independent and integrated modules which can be activated according to specific operational needs. &lt;br&gt; One of the latest module created and already available is the generation of NeTEx datasets starting from the operational data collected by public transport operators. For this purpose, Motus receives the input data starting from a GTFS and it is able to enrich  these data with further relevant information such as contracts, vehicles. Then Motus transforms these data into the NeTEx Italian profile.&lt;br&gt; '''Data model:''' the database is designed according to Transmodel specifications, European reference standard (EN12896) for public  transport. ||Italian || ||
|-
|}

== Journey planning engine ==

{| class="wikitable" style="width: 60%;"
!  Name
! Availability
! Description
! Profile
! License
|-
| style="text-align:center | '''[http://docs.opentripplanner.org/en/dev-2.x/Netex-Norway/ OpenTripPlanner]''' || style="text-align:center |✅||Timetable and shortest path journey planner supporting reading various input formats including GTFS and NeTEx. || Nordic || Apache 2.0
|-
| style="text-align:center | '''[https://openmove.com/technology/trip-planning/ OpenMove]''' ||style="text-align:center | ✅ ||Multimodal, intermodal trip planner with real-time capabilities, step-by-step instructions, fare system, and compatibility with market standards. ||  ||
|-
|}

==Planning system supporting native NeTEx export ==

{| class="wikitable" style="width: 25%;"
!Name
!Availability
!Developped by
!Profile
!Additional documentation
|-
|style="text-align:center | [https://www.giro.ca/en-ca/our-solutions/segments/public-transport/ Hastus] || style="text-align:center |✅ || Giro || Nordic &lt;br&gt; Dutch || Dutch patch: https://github.com/skinkie/hastus 
|-
|style="text-align:center |  [https://www.trapezegroup.com.au/solutions/intelligent-transport-systems-bus Intelligent Transport Systems (ITS) for Bus]  || style="text-align:center |✅|| Trapeze  ||EPIP Nordic  || Blog post: https://www.trapezegroup.com.au/blog/its-netex-bus-data-transfer-exchange 
|-
| style="text-align:center | [https://www.datagrafikk.no/?tag=dgbuss  DG Buss] || style="text-align:center |✅ || Datagrafikk  || Nordic || 
|-
| style="text-align:center | [https://www.trapezegroup.com.au/solutions/planning-and-scheduling-rail  Planning &amp; Scheduling for Train]  ||style="text-align:center |✅ || Trapeze ||Nordic ||
|-
| style="text-align:center | [https://www.ivu.com/solutions#c4826  IVU.suite] || style="text-align:center |⏳ || IVU for public transport ||Nordic ||Blog post: https://www.ivu.com/all-references/references/delfi-migrates-to-ivucloud
|-
| style="text-align:center | [https://turnit.com/ Turnit Ride] ||style="text-align:center |✅ ||Turnit for public transport ||Nordic ||
|-
|style="text-align:center | Nplan ||style="text-align:center |✅ ||Entur for public transport ||Nordic || backend: https://github.com/entur/uttu  &lt;br&gt; frontend: https://github.com/entur/enki 
|-
| style="text-align:center | [https://www.hacon.de/en/portfolio/timetable-construction-disposition/  TPs Suite] ||style="text-align:center | ✅ ||Hacon ||Nordic ||
|}

= NeTEx part 5 for 🆕 modes =

NeTEx Part 5 is an extension to the NeTEx data exchange format that is specifically designed for publishing data about "alternative modes" of transportation, such as car sharing, cycle sharing, carpooling, and car/cycle rental. It is primarily oriented towards static data, such as the service that is offered and the associated infrastructure.

''NeTEx Part 5 is now available as '''CEN/TS 16614-5:2022 (E)'''''
[[File:NeTEx-part5.png|400px|right|]]

{| class="wikitable" style="width: 50%;"
|-
!
!Description
|-
| '''[https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx/tree/master/xsd/netex_part_5 Technical artefacts]''' || The XML schema (XSD) for NeTEx Part 5 New Modes. Examples are also provided, along with other useful documentation.
|-
| '''[https://data4pt.org/w/images/5/5b/Canonical_mapping_-_NeTEx_and_SIRI_new_modes_with_GBFS.pdf Canonical mapping with GBFS]'''
| The EU-funded project DATA4PT and MobilityData experts have released a high-level mapping between the General Bikeshare Feed Specification (GBFS) and Transmodel to support better interoperability of shared mobility data feeds.
|-
|}

= References =

{| class="wikitable" style="width: 35%;"
|-
!Name
!Description
|-
| '''[https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx NeTEx-CEN GitHub]'''
| Find xsd, examples and relevant documentation on NeTEx schema
|-
| '''[https://github.com/NeTEx-CEN/NeTEx-Profile-EPIP NeTEx EPIP profile GitHub]'''
| Find xsd and relevant documentation dedicated on NeTEx EPIP schema
|-
| '''[https://netex-cen.eu/ NeTEx Website]'''
| Find general information on NeTEx project
|-
|}</text>
      <sha1>kk2ojul1ytyi5lmhi5ici18rc68rhns</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>NeTEx software</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18</id>
    <revision>
      <id>105</id>
      <parentid>103</parentid>
      <timestamp>2021-01-11T13:33:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Skinkie</username>
        <id>12</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>GTFS2NeTExFr</comment>
      <origin>105</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="3654" sha1="3cxltgo19c6ck88tnjc0v38nfyu1wf4" xml:space="preserve">
The following list of software is known to support NeTEx. We distinguish between different categories that may later receive a list of key performance indicators.

==Conversion of NeTEx between other formats==
{| class="wikitable"
!colspan="1"|Name
!colspan="1"|Availability
!colspan="1"|Description
!colspan="1"|Profile
!colspan="1"|License
!colspan="1"|URL
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[gtfs2netexfr]]
|Available
|Export GTFS data to NeTEx.
|French
|
|https://github.com/CanalTP/transit_model/tree/master/gtfs2netexfr
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[hastus]]
|Available
|Giro Hastus OIG script to export NeTEx from a system, in addition can export crew operations.
|Dutch, Norwegian(?)
|AGPL-3.0
|https://github.com/skinkie/hastus
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[josm-plugin-netex-converter]]
|Available
|Export OpenStreetMap pedestrian routing information into NeTEx.
|
|GPL 2.0
|https://gitlab.com/labiangashi/josm-plugin-netex-converter/
|-
|}

==Data Validation tools==
{| class="wikitable"
!colspan="1"|Name
!colspan="1"|Availability
!colspan="1"|Description
!colspan="1"|Profile
!colspan="1"|License
!colspan="1"|URL
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[XMLlint]]
|Available
|XML syntax validation, XSD schema validation and constraint checking.
|All
|MIT
|http://www.xmlsoft.org/
|-
|}

==Language bindings and software development aids==
{| class="wikitable"
!colspan="6"|NeTEx XML bindings
|-
!colspan="1"|Name
!colspan="1"|Availability
!colspan="1"|Description
!colspan="1"|Profile
!colspan="1"|License
!colspan="1"|URL
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[netex-java-model]]
|Available
|NeTEx XML bindings for Java, with additions to map temporal types to native objects.
|Any
|EUPL
|https://github.com/entur/netex-java-model
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[netex-csharp-model]]
|Not Available
|NeTEx XML bindings for C#. Currently being researched with a variety of tools.&lt;br&gt;Contact DATA4PT if you have questions or have found the golden egg.
|Any
|
|
|-
|}

==Editing /Management  &amp; visuallisation tools for  NeTEx data==
{| class="wikitable"
!colspan="1"|Name
!colspan="1"|Availability
!colspan="1"|Description
!colspan="1"|Profile
!colspan="1"|License
!colspan="1"|URL
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[Chouette]]
|Available
|Java based NeTEx tools, transforms between profiles and standards (NeTEx, GTFS, Neptune).
|EPIP
|Apache 2.0
|https://enroute.mobi/produits/chouette/
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[mobilitx]]
|Available
|
|
|
|https://mobilitx.diginext.fr/
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[mobiref]]
|Available
|
|
|
|https://www.lumiplan.com/produit/mobiref/
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[NeTEx Reader]]
|In Development
|C# based XML tool, based on Giro Hastus XSD.
|Dutch
|
|https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mpb_1Y9uR5k
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[netexconv2]]
|In Development
|Java based NeTEx tools, transforms between profiles and standards (NeTEx, DINO, HAFAS, KV1, GTFS).
|Dutch, Norwegian
|
|
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[IVU.cloud]]
|Available
|
|EPIP
|
|https://www.ivu.com/news/news/article/delfi-successfully-migrates-to-ivucloud.html
|-
|}

==NeTEx data enabled==
{| class="wikitable"
!colspan="1"|Name
!colspan="1"|Availability
!colspan="1"|Description
!colspan="1"|Profile
!colspan="1"|License
!colspan="1"|URL
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[OpenTripPlanner]]
|Available
|Timetable and shortest path journey planner supporting reading various input formats including GTFS and NeTEx.
|Norwegian 
|Apache 2.0
|http://docs.opentripplanner.org/en/dev-2.x/Netex-Norway/
|-
|}</text>
      <sha1>3cxltgo19c6ck88tnjc0v38nfyu1wf4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Portugal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>79</id>
    <revision>
      <id>631</id>
      <parentid>578</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-10-08T13:20:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Admin moved page [[Draft:Portugal]] to [[Portugal]]</comment>
      <origin>578</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="3080" sha1="s1zlfx95iyg9wknz6gti00c3ueq34lb" xml:space="preserve">== Overview in the National Level ==
In Portugal, AMP (Metropolitan Area of Porto) is working with native NeTEx, and it is anticipated that other PTAs will soon adopt and use it as well. AMP has extensively utilized the validator, while TML (Metropolitan Transport of Lisbon) and Carris (one of the largest PTOs in Portugal) have also employed it to validate some NeTEx information.

Regarding the use of the NAP, the number of users has been growing considerably, and the available information is highly diverse. It encompasses public transportation (both roadway and railway), electric charging points, Zones of Conditional Automobile Access (UVAR), loading and unloading zones, scooter parks, parking lots, taxi ranks, bus lanes, passenger drop-off and pick-up zones, bicycle parking, motorcycle parks, cycle paths, and other related information.

== Use cases ==

=== Description ===
The Metropolitan Area of Porto covers 2,041 km², with a population of 1.76 million, including 76,000 university students, which represents 20% of Portugal's university population. As a Transport Authority, responsibilities include overseeing bus services operated by private companies, which covers:

* Planning (routes, interconnections, frequencies, coverage, etc.)
* Establishing ticketing, fees, pricing, and regulations
* Managing contracts
* Handling payments related to contractual obligations (bonuses/penalties)
* Providing public information (indirectly, to other public or private entities that are better positioned to integrate the information)

To meet these requirements, the exchange of detailed information is essential. NeTEx has been chosen for data exchange between stakeholders due to its advantages:

* Comprehensive coverage of all transport system areas
* Object-oriented data model
* Version control mechanisms
* Supports transmission as both payload and file
* Compliant with the Portuguese NAP standard (IMT)
* A fully recognized European standard since 2006

=== Architecture ===
The platform is designed as a collection of microservices, with information exchange between specialized applications managed through NeTEx. This architecture allows for the replacement of any application with a commercial, internal, or open-source solution, provided that it supports exporting or importing data in the NeTEx format.
[[File:Portugal schema.png|thumb|656x656px|center|Flux diagram of NeTEx exchange]]
=== Use cases ===
PLIM is the name of the platform where all internal information is communicated using NeTEx. It produces NeTEx, GTFS, SIRI, and GTFS-feed formats for dissemination to National Access Points (NAP).

=== Outcome ===
Netex will be seen as the base for information sharing as long as it covers all the aspects of the organisation needs. Potential extensions might be considered. 

In the future, it is hoped that comprehensive transport information will be available through NeTEx and SIRI via collaborative sharing. This information will enable companies and individual projects to develop applications that address global needs or specific interests.</text>
      <sha1>s1zlfx95iyg9wknz6gti00c3ueq34lb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>SIRI</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11</id>
    <revision>
      <id>492</id>
      <parentid>482</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-03-29T13:21:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anasfou</username>
        <id>5</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>492</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="7039" sha1="o7q9yujf9oxq3evl89xzqg08golhqgm" xml:space="preserve">
= SIRI overview 🔍 =
== What is SIRI? ==

SIRI is a European standard that enables '''real-time information''' about public transportation to be shared between different '''computer systems'''. It is used by many different organizations, including public transportation operators, traffic management agencies, and travel information providers.

SIRI was established as European standard in October 2006. It is a CEN (Comité Européen de Normalisation) and Technical Standard

== SIRI formats ==

SIRI is a protocol for data exchange between two '''IT systems for real-time information'''. Data can be exchanged via: 

*'''XML files''' (over TCP/IP or via SOAP/WSDL) 

*'''REST/JSON''' (over HTTP) using SIRI-Lite interface 

''Note: SIRI-Lite is a subset of SIRI focusing on the most frequently requested information for open data feeds.''

== What can SIRI be used for? ==

SIRI can be used for a variety of purposes, such as:

*Providing real-time arrival information at bus stops and train stations
*Tracking the progress of individual vehicles
*Managing the movement of buses between different areas
*Synchronizing connections between different services
*Exchanging planned and real-time timetable updates
*Distributing status messages about the operation of services
*Providing performance information to operational history and other management systems

== Benefits of SIRI ==

SIRI has made a significant contribution to improving the efficiency and reliability of public transportation across Europe. It is now used by millions of people every day to plan their journeys and get real-time information about the services they are using.

For example, SIRI can help you to:

*Avoid missing a bus or train
*Plan your journey more efficiently
*Get real-time information about disruptions to services
*Find the best way to travel between different locations


ℹ️ To find out more about the '''SIRI data model''', please visit the [http://www.transmodel-cen.eu/standards/siri/ Transmodel page] and [https://siri-cen.eu/ SIRI page].



= Software &amp; tools 🧰 =

The following list of software is known to support NeTEx. We distinguish between different categories that may later receive a list of key performance indicators.

== XML tools ==
General purpose XML tools can be used to work with the SIRI XML schema and XML documents that conform to it.

{| class="wikitable" style="width : 10%"
|-
! XML tools
! Description
|-
|[http://www.altova.com/xmlspy.html XML SPY] || commercial
|-
|[http://www.oxygenxml.com/ Oxygen]|| commercial
|-
|[http://www.garshol.priv.no/download/xmltools/ List of tools] || open-source
|-
{| class="wikitable"

== Conversion and connectors tools ==

{| class="wikitable" style="width :60%"
! colspan="1" | Name
! Availability
! colspan="1" |Description
! colspan="1" |Profile
! colspan="1" |License
|-
| style="text-align:center |'''[https://github.com/entur/anshar Anshar]''' ||style="text-align:center |✅ || Java based tool to connect, validate and redistribute SIRI. (Act as a national aggreagation hub for all SIRI feeds in Norway)  || Norwegian ||EUPL
|-
|style="text-align:center | '''[https://github.com/OneBusAway/onebusaway-siri OneBusAway SIRI]''' || style="text-align:center |✅ ||A set of tools to connect to and convert SIRI.  ||  ||Apache-2.0
|-
|style="text-align:center | [https://bitbucket.org/enroute-mobi/ara/src/master/ ara] || style="text-align:center |✅ ||A set of tools to connect, convert and store SIRI, SIRI-Lite. || ||Apache-2.0
|-
|style="text-align:center | [https://github.com/afimb/irys irys] ||style="text-align:center |✅ ||A set of tools to connect and redistribute SIRI. || || CeCILL-B
|-
|[https://mobilitx.diginext.fr/ Diginext/CS-Group] ||style="text-align:center |✅ || || ||
|-
|style="text-align:center | [https://www.lumiplan.com/produit/mobiflux/ Soridis/Lumiplan] || style="text-align:center |✅ || || ||
|-
|style="text-align:center | [https://qommute.com Qommute] ||style="text-align:center |✅ || || ||
|-
|}

== Data validation tools ==

{| class="wikitable" style="width : 30%"
!  Name
! Availability
!  Description
! Profile
! License
|-
| style="text-align:center |'''[https://github.com/department-for-transport-BODS/bods BODS]''' || style="text-align:center |✅ ||Validator of TransXChange and SIRI-VM ||All ||Open Source  
|-
|}

==Producers from CAD/AVL==

{| class="wikitable" style="width : 30%"
!colspan="1"|Name
!colspan="1"|Availability
!colspan="1"|Description
!colspan="1"|Profile
!colspan="1"|License
|-
|style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[https://www.ivu.com/products-and-solutions/ivusuite/passenger-information.html IVU.realtime] ||style="text-align:center;"  |✅ ||Producer of realtime data. || ||Commercial
|-
|style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[https://www.initse.com/fileadmin/user_upload/Content/3_Solutions/3_Operations/MOBILE-ITCS_us.pdf Mobile-ITCS] ||style="text-align:center;"  |✅ ||Producer of realtime data. || ||Commercial
|-
|style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|INEO ||style="text-align:center;"  |✅ || || ||
|-
|style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|Navocap ||style="text-align:center;"  |✅ || || ||
|-
|style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[https://zenbus.fr/ ZenBus] ||style="text-align:center;"  |✅ ||Producer of realtime data. || ||Commercial
|-
|style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[https://www.ratpsmartsystems.com/hopen-go/ IXXI/RATP Smart System] ||style="text-align:center;"  |✅ ||Producer of realtime data. || ||Commercial
|-
|style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|Alstom ||style="text-align:center;"  |✅ ||Producer of realtime data. || ||Commercial
|-
|}

= SIRI extension for 🆕 Modes =
In line with '''NeTEx Part 5''', corresponding extensions are made in SIRI for real time data such as current number of available vehicles, current number of spaces available to bring back a vehicle or to park, etc. SIRI also provide updates of positions (typically for free floating vehicles). The SIRI Facility Monitoring (FM) service is extended to provide this counted information

{| class="wikitable" style="width: 40%;"
|-
!
!Description
|-
| '''[https://www.netex-cen.eu/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/NeTEx-extension-for-New-Modes-Detailed-Scope-v04.pdf NeTEx extension for New Modes]''' || Scope and overview
|-
| '''[https://data4pt.org/w/images/5/5b/Canonical_mapping_-_NeTEx_and_SIRI_new_modes_with_GBFS.pdf Canonical mapping with GBFS]'''
| The EU-funded project DATA4PT and MobilityData experts have released a high-level mapping between the General Bikeshare Feed Specification (GBFS) and Transmodel to support better interoperability of shared mobility data feeds.
|-
|}

= References =

{| class="wikitable" style="width : 30%"
|-
!Name
!Description
|-
| '''[https://github.com/SIRI-CEN/SIRI SIRI-CEN GitHub]'''
| Find xsd, examples and relevant documentation on SIRI schema
|-
| '''[https://www.transmodel-cen.eu/ Transmodel website]'''
| European data model for public transport information
|-
| '''[https://www.siri-cen.eu/ SIRI website]'''
| Official SIRI website
|-
|}</text>
      <sha1>o7q9yujf9oxq3evl89xzqg08golhqgm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>SIRI software</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19</id>
    <revision>
      <id>102</id>
      <parentid>99</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-12-08T09:22:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>102</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2365" sha1="5d7b5pkl8vhbibmw6v9llitgbsxvgsf" xml:space="preserve">
The following list of software is known to support NeTEx. We distinguish between different categories that may later receive a list of key performance indicators.

==Conversion and connectors to SIRI software and between other formats==
{| class="wikitable"
!colspan="1"|Name
!colspan="1"|Availability
!colspan="1"|Description
!colspan="1"|Profile
!colspan="1"|License
!colspan="1"|URL
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[OneBusAway SIRI]]
|Available
|A set of tools to connect to and convert SIRI.
|
|Apache-2.0
|https://github.com/OneBusAway/onebusaway-siri
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[ara]]
|Available
|A set of tools to connect, convert and store SIRI, SIRI-Lite.
|
|Apache-2.0
|https://bitbucket.org/enroute-mobi/ara/src/master/
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[irys]]
|Available
|A set of tools to connect and redistribute SIRI.
|
|CeCILL-B
|https://github.com/afimb/irys
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[Diginext/CS-Group]]
|Available
|
|
|
|https://mobilitx.diginext.fr/
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[Soridis/Lumiplan]]
|Available
|
|
|
|https://www.lumiplan.com/produit/mobiflux/
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[Qommute]]
|Available
|
|
|
|https://qommute.com
|-
|}

==Producers from CAD/AVL==
{| class="wikitable"
!colspan="1"|Name
!colspan="1"|Availability
!colspan="1"|Description
!colspan="1"|Profile
!colspan="1"|License
!colspan="1"|URL
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[IVU.realtime]]
|Available
|Producer of realtime data.
|
|Commercial
|https://www.ivu.com/products-and-solutions/ivusuite/passenger-information.html
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[Mobile-ITCS]]
|Available
|Producer of realtime data.
|
|Commercial
|https://www.initse.com/fileadmin/user_upload/Content/3_Solutions/3_Operations/MOBILE-ITCS_us.pdf
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[INEO]]
|Available
|
|
|
|
|-
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[Navocap]]
|Available
|
|
|
|
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[ZenBus]]
|Available
|Producer of realtime data.
|
|Commercial
|https://zenbus.fr/
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[IXXI/RATP Smart System]]
|Available
|Producer of realtime data.
|
|Commercial
|https://www.ratpsmartsystems.com/hopen-go/
|-
!style="text-align:left;" rowspan="1"|[[Alsthom]]
|Available
|Producer of realtime data.
|
|Commercial
|
|-
|}</text>
      <sha1>5d7b5pkl8vhbibmw6v9llitgbsxvgsf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Slovenia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>89</id>
    <revision>
      <id>625</id>
      <parentid>597</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-10-08T12:55:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Admin moved page [[Draft:Slovenia]] to [[Slovenia]]</comment>
      <origin>597</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="5354" sha1="t7r0l54antyec7f351ai8apucoma54e" xml:space="preserve">== Overview in the National Level ==
Adoption and implementation of standards for digital mobility ecosystems in Slovenia is driven by the requirements of the EU Delegated Regulations for the provision of multi-modal travel information (DU 2017/1926 and DU 2024/490) and the established technical specifications to ensure the efficient exchange of data between data owners, data suppliers, data aggregators, mobility data publishers and travel information service providers. National Access Point (NAP, nap.si) serves as a technical platform aimed to obtain, analyse, process, manage and publish data for end users and product developers at the NAP.

The governance of the NAP is responsibility of the National Traffic Management Centre (NCUP, ncup.si), as part of the Ministry of Infrastructure.

As part of the national NCUP-2 project Transmodel based technical standards NeTEx and SIRI are implemented. 

== Use cases ==
Under the coordination of the NCUP following national developments are related to this report:

# Establishment of IT services for the implementation of the NeTEx National Profile
# Implementation of dynamic multimodal data according to the SIRI standard specification
# Slovenian Multimodal Journey Planner: SiMO

=== Description ===
All projects mentioned in this report have national (Slovenian) coverage. The NAP integrates all relevant data in terms of transport infrastructure (roads, rail, seaway) and service providers (public transport operators, mobility data service providers) with all modalities nationwide. Recent developments also emphasize standardized data collection for private modes like cycling and alternative modes like car-pooling where NeTEx, SIRI and DATEXII are being identified as best candidates.

=== Architecture ===
The IT architecture of the above mentioned projects 1, 2 and 3 can be can be summarised in the following data pipeline (see the diagram on Figure 1) It shows the flow of multimodal mobility data from data owners that can use intermediary data suppliers providing input for NCUP as the main data aggregator. The aggregated data is then prepared for utilization at NAP. The NAP data can be further processed by different travel and mobility information services providers.
[[File:Digital mobility data ecosystem at NCUP Slovenia.png|center|thumb|568x568px|Digital mobility data ecosystem at NCUP]]

=== Use cases ===
In the section the three projects related to NeTEx, SIRI and OJP are described

==== National NeTEx profile ====
In July 2021 the Slovenian National Profile for NeTEx v 1.0 was specified based on the standardised NeTEx EPIP (SIST-TS CEN/TS 16614-4:2020, NeTEx - Part 4: Passenger Information European Profile). In August 2024 preparation of the Slovenian National Profile for NeTEx v 2.0 started. Requirements for the task are to upgrade the profile by checking its compliance with the EU Delegated Regulations for the provision of multi-modal travel information (DU 2017/1926 and DU 2024/490).

==== SIRI implementation ====
In 2023, the SIRI implementation from 2020 was upgraded. The SIRI web service is installed within the NCUP's digital mobility ecosystem. The web service module for preparation of the SIRI files was upgraded to add static timetable data (from NeTEx) to the dynamic vehicle location data that operate within the national integrated public transport system (IJPP). The SIRI web service retrieves the references of the following NeTEx timetable objects: LineRef, PublishedLineName, VehicleJourneyRef, VehicleJourneyName, JourneyPatternRef, JourneyPatternName, RouteRef, OperatorRef, JourneyParts.

The current situation after the implementation of the project in 2023 is shown in Figure 1, where it can be seen that the SIRI modules have been installed throughout the entire information pipeline, from the data owners and suppliers (for the time being the IJPP system), to the data aggregator NCUP, and the national access point NAP.si.

==== SIMO.si ====
The Slovenian Multimodal Journey Planner (SiMO - Slovenian mobility, simo.si, Figure 1) is a national solution for improved sustainable travel choices based on reliable and accurate data.

Managed by the NCUP, and supported by data from our NAP, SiMO offers comprehensive route planning that integrates various modes of transport – personal, scheduled, and demand-based – into a single, user-friendly platform. SiMO eliminates fragmented information by gathering all travel options in one service, enabling users to explore, compare, and better plan their journeys. Accurate schedules, real-time updates on routes, equipment and accessibility information improve the travel experience, with delays, disruption and exceptional circumstances being reported to users, as incidents, roadworks or severe weather warnings.

=== Outcome ===
The Transmodel family of standardised technical specifications (NeTEx, SIRI, OJP) is well used in the Slovenian multimodal services reality. The initial implementations started in 2020 and are now being upgraded to latest requirements in the EU Delegated regulations. Until the end of 2024 the developments are expected to improve the multimodal mobility services experience in Slovenia.

Additionally, synergies with other ITS projects are created, such as implementation of the C-ITS (benefiting from SIRI), Traffic GIS (benefiting from NeTEx), etc.</text>
      <sha1>t7r0l54antyec7f351ai8apucoma54e</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Support Request</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16</id>
    <revision>
      <id>75</id>
      <parentid>74</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-11-05T09:31:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>75</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1135" sha1="sarrhbsvxaeeze1lfsikqbc1a4kb4bn" xml:space="preserve">One of the main objectives of the DATA4PT project is to support entities with the implementation of data models NeTEx, Transmodel, and SIRI. By doing this, DATA4PT aims to enhance the interoperability of information travel services in the public transport sector.

=== Who can ask for support? ===

Everybody with an interest into public transport, data and travel information services is welcome to submit a request for support. DATA4PT provides support to entities responsible for National Access Points (NAP) when implementing multimodal travel information services (MMTIS) according to EU data standards. We also support public transport authorities, operators, data producers and data consumers, and the IT industry.

=== How can I ask for support? ===

Simple: you can submit your technical request or requirement below. The DATA4PT technical Expert Team will process any incoming request and reply through appropriate channels, depending on the issue’s nature. If development is required, we will contact you to discuss a solution. 



:[[File:Support request.png|100px|link=https://data4pt-project.eu/requests-requirements/]]</text>
      <sha1>sarrhbsvxaeeze1lfsikqbc1a4kb4bn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Sweden</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>76</id>
    <revision>
      <id>623</id>
      <parentid>584</parentid>
      <timestamp>2024-10-08T12:54:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Admin moved page [[Draft:Sweden]] to [[Sweden]]</comment>
      <origin>584</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4959" sha1="f9xayegzhvfcb00qrrht8b5pvqjfg9i" xml:space="preserve">==Overview in the National Level==
The National project “Open Data” has been the foundation in implementing NeTEx and SIRI (Nordic Profile) in accordance with MMTIS in Sweden. The solution consists of an integration platform (STIP) where national imported Public Transport data in Noptis DOI/DII (Static data) and Noptis ROI (Realtime data) as well as Transport and MPK – proprietary formats, is translated into NeTEx and SIRI (as well as GTFS and GTFS-R). The translated data is published at the NAP (Trafiklab.se) and used within the National ticketing Distribution System as well as various traffic information services such as Skånetrafikens OTP2 (Open Trip Planner).

==Use cases ==

There are two main use cases in Sweden where Transmodel based standards are implemented and used. 

#'''National ticket Distribution System, Sweden''' (all PTA´s and PTO´s). New national ticketing distribution based on booking standard OSDM with traffic data in NeTEx format.  Sweden is the first in Europe with a distributed ecosystem connected to multiple booking systems. The system is built on the open and international booking standard OSDM-Online, developed by the International Union of Railways (UIC). The system is fed with Public Transport data based on NeTEx (Nordic Profile). With this competition-neutral standards as a foundation, all producers in both Sweden and Europe have the opportunity to connect. Consequently, the system will have multiple booking systems linked to it. The system is being developed in collaboration with Turnit, an Estonian company with experience in standards within the railway industry in Europe.
#'''Open Trip Planner Skåne, Sweden'''. New trip planner developed on open standard OTP2 for regional travelling and cross boarder travelling purposes. Skåne is the 3rd largest region (PTA) in Sweden with Public Transport including city buses (incl. BRT) and regional trains.

===Architecture===

==== National ticket Distribution System ====
The new '''National ticket Distribution System, Sweden''' infrastructure creates favorable conditions for the continued development of the ticket collaboration Resplus. The service will also enable more secure and widely validatable tickets when implemented. This, in turn, will contribute to increased safety and secured revenue. The system is being developed in collaboration with Turnit, an Estonian company with experience in standards within the railway industry in Europe. The new infrastructure is built on four essential components, with communication between these components based on the international and open OSDM-Online standard (Open Sales and Distribution Model).
# A "data warehouse" where the majority of Samtrafiken's partners will store their ticket products. This is where the offerings of transportation companies are entered, and it is from here that the service retrieves the inventory.
# The sales tool Samtrafiken TRAID and a sales API. In TRAID, retailers can directly book journeys, suitable for those retailers with a need for manual sales management (such as kiosks, stores, or call centers) or as a complement to web sales. Retailers and producers wishing to sell through their own sales tools (such as websites or apps) can choose to access the inventory via API.
# Travel search for all saleable ground-based collective transport.
# A central service, a so-called distribution hub, which retrieves, combines, and distributes ticket products from both Samtrafiken's data warehouse and external data warehouses for partners with their booking systems.

==== Open Trip Planner Skåne ====
'''The Skåne OpenTripPlanner''' (OTP2) is a server-side Java application that is primarily designed to interpret and combine map, transit service, and other mobility data sets, providing API endpoints that receive user origins and destinations and return trip plans to other applications along with vector map tiles, stop departures, and other rider information. In other words, OTP is a backend application that can work with other frontend user interfaces. OTP is an open standard and works with your website, mobile app, physical signage or other applications in order to provide relevant customer information and meaningful trip plans to riders.

=== Outcome ===
The '''National ticket Distribution System''' and '''Open Trip Planner Skåne OTP2''' are implemented and in operation with minor operational problems to fix as well as ongoing further developments. Both implementations are built on open and international standards provided with Public Transport data like NeTEx and Siri. With this competition-neutral standards as a foundation, all producers in both Sweden and Europe have the opportunity to connect. This provides significant benefits for travelers, making it easier to access, plan, and book train journeys with multiple transport operators, including competing companies, both in national and reginal level as well as to/from Europe.</text>
      <sha1>f9xayegzhvfcb00qrrht8b5pvqjfg9i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Switzerland</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>98</id>
    <revision>
      <id>731</id>
      <parentid>730</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-04-17T16:22:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anasfou</username>
        <id>5</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Overview in the National Level */</comment>
      <origin>731</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4696" sha1="6eikqfvu5w18f6necijebia5y69uq3z" xml:space="preserve">== Overview in the National Level ==
In Switzerland, the [https://www.bav.admin.ch/en/the-fot Federal Office of Transportation] (FOT) provides the Swiss National Access Point (NAP) called “[https://opentransportdata.swiss/en/ opentransportdata.swiss]”. Additionally, a national, open, non-discriminatory trip planner has been made available named after its interface standard “Open Journey Planner” (OJP-System). A demo is available [https://opentdatach.github.io/ojp-demo-app/search here]. 

It is important to note that the published data covers primarily conventional public transport. The goal is to extend to other forms of transport, too. All road related data is handled by the [https://www.astra.admin.ch/astra/en/home.html Federal Roads Office in Switzerland] (FEDRO), while all geographical and topological information is gathered by the Federal Office of Topography ([https://www.swisstopo.admin.ch/en swisstopo]). On this page we focus on the FOT related data.

Via [https://opentransportdata.swiss/en/ opentransportdata.swiss] and OJP, Switzerland provides the following data standards for Switzerland: 
{| class="wikitable" style="width: 50%;"
|-
| style="text-align: center;" | Timetables
| [https://www.oev-info.ch/sites/default/files/2024-05/NeTEx_Core-Realisation_Guide_TP_Suisse-v1.00.pdf NeTEx – Swiss Profile]

[https://www.oev-info.ch/sites/default/files/2024-04/gtfs_profil_switzerland_version_0_16_en.pdf GTFS – Swiss Profile]

[https://www.oev-info.ch/sites/default/files/2023-07/hrdf_2_0_5_e.pdf HRDF – Swiss Profile]
|-
| style="text-align: center;" | On demand
| [https://www.oev-info.ch/sites/default/files/2024-07/Fachkonzept%20On-Demand_v2.1_en.pdf NeTEx]

[https://www.oev-info.ch/sites/default/files/2024-04/gtfs_profil_switzerland_version_0_16_en.pdf GTFS Flex]
|-
| style="text-align: center;" | Realtime data
| [https://www.oev-info.ch/sites/default/files/2023-04/siri_realisation-guide_pt_ch_v0.9.0.pdf SIRI-ET/PT – Swiss Profile]

[https://www.oev-info.ch/sites/default/files/2024-04/gtfs_profil_switzerland_version_0_16_en.pdf GTFS Realtime – Swiss Profile]
|-
| style="text-align: center;" | Events
| [https://www.oev-info.ch/sites/default/files/2024-07/realization_guide_siri-sx_oev_schweiz_v1.0.pdf SIRI-SX – Swiss Profile]

[https://www.oev-info.ch/sites/default/files/2024-04/gtfs_profil_switzerland_version_0_16_en.pdf GTFS Service Alerts]
|-
| style="text-align: center;" | Routing
| OJP 1.0 – Swiss Profile ([https://www.oev-info.ch/sites/default/files/2023-05/open_journey_planner_ojp_de_v1_eng.pdf Documentation], [https://opentransportdata.swiss/en/cookbook/open-journey-planner-ojp/ API])

OJP 2.0 – Swiss Profile (Documentation: Work In Progress, [https://opentransportdata.swiss/en/cookbook/open-journey-planner-ojp/ API])
|-
| style="text-align: center;" | Fares
| OJP-Fare – [https://opentransportdata.swiss/en/cookbook/open-journey-planner-ojp/ojp-fare/ Swiss Profile]
|}

== Use cases ==

=== Description ===

* NeTEx  is not yet broadly used by Swiss (public) transport operators. The provided export is primarily used by the neighboring countries and their larger transport operators (e.g., SNCF in France). The reason being its complexity (you need experts to understand and apply it) and multiplicity (substitution classes and similar constructs make simple adaptations difficult). Data exchange for timetables is mostly done by HRDF.
* SIRI-SX is being actively used to represent disruptions, while SIRI-ET and -PT have only recently been introduced and are not widely adapted (currently, mainly VDV 454 and 453 are used).
* The GTFS standards are used most by small and medium-sized mobility providers.
* Alongside the use of the routing service, the OJP standard is being increasingly adapted by transport operators, especially with the introduction of OJP 2.0.

=== Architecture ===
The following figure provides an overview of the public transport data being centrally provided and processed for the various previously introduced data categories. 

Short translation:

* Ereignisdaten = event data
* Echtzeitdaten = realtime data
* Fahrplandaten = timetable data
* Stammdaten = master data
* Datendrehscheibe = data exchange hub

[[File:Swiss architecture.png|center|thumb|674x674px]]

=== Use cases ===
The provided data is used for all public transport customer information systems in Switzerland. 

Furthermore, a set of showcases created with the opentransportdata.swiss data can be found [https://data.opentransportdata.swiss/showcase here]:

=== Outcome ===
The easier the standards are to use and to adapt, the more they are accepted and used by transport operators and mobility service providers.</text>
      <sha1>6eikqfvu5w18f6necijebia5y69uq3z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Transmodel</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4</id>
    <revision>
      <id>109</id>
      <parentid>30</parentid>
      <timestamp>2021-01-22T13:23:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Admin</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>109</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1299" sha1="7mhull23nt54b0a60sgvtehj57ux715" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Transmodel.png|right|link=http://www.transmodel-cen.eu/]]
'''Transmodel''' is the short name for the European Standard “Public Transport Reference Data Model” (EN 12896). It contributes to improving a number of features of public transport information and service management: in particular, the standard facilitates interoperability between information processing systems of the transport operators and agencies.

Public transport services rely increasingly on information systems to ensure reliable, efficient operation and widely accessible, accurate passenger information. These systems are used for a range of specific purposes: setting schedules and timetables, managing vehicle fleets, issuing tickets and receipts, providing real time information on service running, and so on.

Transmodel has an important strategic role for European Public Transport data. Under the ITS Directive (Priority Action A ), by 2019 all EC member states must make their data available under Transmodel based standard formats such as NeTEx and SIRI. Transmodel is also being used to harmonise the TAP TSI rail standards into a uniform pan-European model, so is of direct relevance to rail carriers.

To find out more about Transmodel, please visit the [http://www.transmodel-cen.eu/ Transmodel website].</text>
      <sha1>7mhull23nt54b0a60sgvtehj57ux715</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
